<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the second voyage to Guiana. Perfourmed and written in the yeare 1596. By Lawrence Kemys, Gent</title>
            <author>Kemys, Lawrence, d. 1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04813</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14947</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109262</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844912</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844912</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9768</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04813)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9768)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 251:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the second voyage to Guiana. Perfourmed and written in the yeare 1596. By Lawrence Kemys, Gent</title>
                  <author>Kemys, Lawrence, d. 1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Dawson, dwelling at the three Cranes in the Vintree, and are to be solde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ ² A-G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The second voyage to Guiana.</note>
                  <note>Variant: with "Keymis" in title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Guyana --  Discovery and exploration --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9768:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9768:1"/>
            <p>A Relation of the <hi>ſecond <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oyage to</hi> Guiana.</p>
            <p>Perfourmed and written in the yeare 1596.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Lawrence Kemys, Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Thomas Dawſon,</hi> dwelling at the three Cranes in the Vintree, and are there to be ſolde.</p>
            <p>1596.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:9768:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>AMORE ET VIRTVTE</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9768:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE APPROOVED, right valorous, and woorthy Knight, Sir Walter Ralegh,</hi> Lord Warden of the Stanneries, Captaine of her Maiesties Guard and her Highneſſe Lieutenant general of the Countie of Cornwall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue heere brieflie ſet downe the effect of this your ſecond Diſcouerie, without anie enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of made wordes: for in this argument, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle ſpeech beſt beſemeth a ſimple truth. Where the affinity of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with your perſon, leadeth me to write of your ſelfe, vnto your ſelfe: that ſmall libertie which I haue therein vſed, ſhall, I doubt not, without offence, or ſiniſter conſtruction, be giuen to the cauſe in hand: which whether it ſuffer not detriment, by attributing leſſe, then of right belongeth: the iudgement be theirs, that vprightly and indifferentlie ſhall weigh
<pb facs="tcp:9768:3"/>
the conſequentes of their euill purpoſe, who in ſeeking to detract from the Authour of theſe Diſcoueries, do ſo much as in them ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, wound, deface, and treade vnder foot the thing it ſelfe. But this is no noueltie, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per only to theſe our dayes. For long ſince it hath bene ſaid.<note place="margin">Pericles.</note> 
               <hi>Laudes eo vſque ſunt tolerabiles, donec ea dicuntur, quae auditores ſe quoque facere poſse existi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant: ſi maiora proferantur: Inuident, non credunt.</hi> The feruent zeale and loyaltie of your mind in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with this birth of ſo honourable expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, as it hath deſerued a recompence farre different ſo needeth it not my poore ſuffrage to endeare the toyle, care, and daunger, that you haue willinglie vndergone for the good and aduauncement of our weale publique. The praiſe-worthines therof doth approoue it ſelfe, &amp; is better read in your liuing doinges, then in my dead vnregarded papers. All that I can wiſh, is that my life were a ſufficient pledge, to iuſtifie, how much more eaſie, and more material, the courſe for the <hi>Guiana</hi> wold be the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others: which requiring greater charge, yeeld not ſo large benefit, and are ſubiect to
<pb facs="tcp:9768:3"/>
more doubtful euents. If vnto their wiſdoms, who ſit in place and authoritie, it ſhal appeare otherwiſe, and that in following of other at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts there is leſſe difficultie, certainer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, &amp; needfuller offence vnto the enemie: the coſt and trauaile, which you haue beſtowed, ſhall not, I hope, bee altogether loſt: if vnto your Honour, I can well prooue, how, and where the amendes is to be had, maugre the force and preuention of all Spaniardes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips to be commanded</hi> in all ſeruice: Law: Kemys.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:9768:4"/>
            <head>To the Fauourers of the Voyage for <hi>Guiana.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N thinges earneſtly deſired, though neuer ſo likelie, we are ſtill ſuſpicious: thinking it more credite to our common wiſdome, to diſcredit moſt noble and profitable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours with diſtruſt; then touch to our valures and ſafeties to lie wilfullie idle. So that howſoeuer an action well and iudiciallie attempted, be eſteemed halfe performed: yet, is this my iealous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt concerning the <hi>Guiana,</hi> that nothing is begun, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all be ended. In this regarde (gentle Reader) I haue preſumed to burthen thine eares, with the weake plea of a good cauſe, and in ſteede of opening it throughlie, to thy prudent conſideration, to note onlie mine own vnſatisfied affection: hoping that becauſe I do name the <hi>Guiana</hi> vnto thee, thou wilt vouchſafe, <hi>hoc nomine,</hi> to vaile and couer all other my defectes in the deſerte of a good meaning. In publiſhing this treatiſe, my labour principallie tendeth to this end: to remooue all fig-leaues from our vnbeleefe; that either it may haue cauſe to ſhake off the colourable preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ignorance: or, if we will not be perſwaded; that our ſelfe-wil may reſt inexcuſable. They that ſhall applie, and conſtrue this my doing, to ſerue the Spaniard his turne ſo well as our owne; in ſo much as it may ſeeme to inſtruct, warne, and arme him: for their ſatisfaction heerein, they muſt not be ignorant, that his eyes in ſeeing our ſhipping there, doe as effectuallie informe him, that manie of our heartes are toward that place: as if it ſhould bee crediblie aduertiſed, by ſome corrupt hireling that we thinke, write and diſcourſe of nothing els. Neither can I imagine, that to conceale our knowledge herein (which to conceale may perhaps prooue, and bee hereafter taken for worſe then paricide) would be of better purpoſe, then to hoodwincke our ſelues, as who would ſay, no man ſhall ſee vs. Beſides:
<pb facs="tcp:9768:4"/>
if the action were whollie to bee effected at her Maieſties charge: then might it at her Highneeſſe pleaſure, be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with ſome other drift, and neuer bee diſcouered, vntill it were acted: But ſince it craueth the approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and purſes of manie Aduenturers: who cannot be ſo prodigall, both of their poſſeſsions and liues as voluntarily to run themſelues out of breath, in purſuing they knowe not what: great reaſon it is, that where aſsiſtance is to be asked, due cauſes bee yeelded, to perſwade &amp; induce them vnto it. The Spaniard is not ſo ſimple, vnſetled, and vncertaine in his determinations; as to build them on our breath, or to make our papers his Bulwarkes; nor ſo ſlowe, as to expect a preſident of our forwardneſſe. His proceedings are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlie ſtrengthened with the trauailes, reportes, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanciall proofs of his own men, that haue aboue 60. yeares beaten round about this buſh. And, to ſay a truth, the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that he hath vſed, in ſending ſo manie ſhips in Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruarie laſt, to people this countrey, and diſappoint vs: as it doth conſequentlie ſhew, that he findeth his chiefeſt force and ſinewes to conſiſt in golde: ſo doth he thereby plainly to our faces exprobate our remiſſneſſe and long deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that in twelue monethes ſpace haue done, or ſought to doe nothing woorthie the ancient fame, and reputation of our Engliſh nation, interreſſed in ſo waightie buſineſſe<note place="margin">In Iune laſt</note> His late prouiſion of a new ſupplie of whole familes to the number of ſixe hundred perſons, bound for <hi>Guiana,</hi> but that it pleaſed God, that by meanes of that right honourable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice moſt reſolutelie performed in the ſea-fight, and ſacking of <hi>Cades,</hi> the ſhips, wherein they ſhould haue beene conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, were conuerted into aſhes: what might it ſignifie? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, as it doth euidentlie prooue, that <hi>El Dorado</hi> hath vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted credite and account in their iudgements: ſo poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it at vs, whileſt we onlie to entertaine idle time, ſit li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening for <hi>Guiana</hi> newes, and inſtantlie forget it, as if it were nought els, but a pleaſing dreame of a golden fancie.
<pb facs="tcp:9768:5"/>
If we with our ſelues ſhall expoſtulate, how this commeth to paſſe that the aduantage wholie reſting on our ſide, in reſpect that <hi>Berrec</hi> was this laſt yeare beaten out, the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try throughlie diſcouered and the Inhabitantes made deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of her ſacred Maieſties happie gouernment; they not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding by entring before vs: haue nowe gotten the ſtart of vs: what may we thinke? ſhall wee iudge that their natiue country is leſſe deare, or more weariſome vnto them, then ours is vnto vs? Their <hi>Peruleri</hi> who going bare and emptie out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> do againe within three or foure years returne from <hi>Peru,</hi> rich and in good eſtate, do apparantlie diſprooue all ſuch conceipts of them. Shall we ſay that they haue more ſpare men to be imployed in ſuch actions? It is no ſecrete to know the contrarie. Are they ſubiect to penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie? In all partes of Chriſtendome, where money is not ſcant, all other things are plentifull. Or is their land not able to ſuſtain their numbers of people? They buy many ſlaues to follow their husbandrie, and themſelues diſdaining baſe idleneſſe, and beggerie, do all honour militarie profeſsion, highlie eſteeming it, in their mercenaries and ſtrangers. Is it then want of abilitie, in thoſe that are willing? lacke of incouragement. Or default of ſpeedie order and direction for thoſe that doe voluntarile offer themſelues, their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and beſt indeuour to further this cauſe; that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs to be thus coated by the Spaniard? The firſt is no queſtion. The latter needeth no anſwere. The profit then by their example to be gathered, is, not to looſe opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie by delay, or to ſeeme fearfull and diſmayed, where there is no cauſe of doubt. For as yet their poſt haſt doth no way preiudice our aduiſed leyſure in ſetting forward, ſince their preparations of <hi>Negroes</hi> to worke in the mynes, their horſes, cattel, and other neceſſaries, may, (by the fauour of God) at our firſt comming, both ſtore vs with quantities of gold oare, and eaſe vs of much trouble, paines, and trauaile. If we ſhould ſuppoſe our ſelues now to liue in the dayes of King
<pb facs="tcp:9768:5"/>
               <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſeuenth of famous memorie and the ſtrange re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of a Weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> or new world abounding with great treaſure ſhould entice vs to beleeue it: perhaps it might be imputed for ſome blame to the grauitie of wiſe men, lightly to be carried with the perſwaſion and hope of a new found <hi>Vtopia,</hi> by ſuch a one as <hi>Columbus</hi> was being an alien and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie wayes ſubiect to ſuſpition. But ſince the penance of that incredulity lyeth euen now heauie on out ſhoulders; the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample forethreatning. I know not what; repentance: and that we haue the perſonall triall of ſo honorable and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient a Reporter, our owne Countriman: let it bee farre from vs to condemne our ſelues in that, which ſo worthilie we reprooue in our predeceſſors; and to let our idle know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge content it ſelfe with naked contemplation like a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren womb in a Monaſterie. We cannot denie that the chiefe commendation of vertue doth conſiſt in action: we truly ſay that <hi>Otium</hi> is <hi>animae viuae ſepultura:</hi> we beleeue, that perfect wiſdome in this mobility of al humain affaires refuſeth not with anie price to purchaſe ſafetie: and wee iuſtlie doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that the Caſtilians from barelegged mountey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners haue attained to their greatneſſe, by labour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie: To ſleep then, becauſe it coſteth nothing, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the preſent time, becauſe it flattereth vs with deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full contentment, &amp; to kiſſe ſecuritie ſaying what euill hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth vnto vs? is the plaine high-way to a fearfull downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall: from which the Lord in his mercie deliuer vs, and giue vs an vnderſtanding heart, in time to ſee, and to ſeeke that, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth vnto our peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:9768:6"/>
            <head>De Guiana, carmen Epicum.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHat worke of honour and eternall name,</l>
               <l>For all the worlde t'enuie and vs t'atchieue,</l>
               <l>Filles me with furie, and giues armed handes</l>
               <l>To my heartes peace, that els would gladlie turne</l>
               <l>My limmes and euery ſence into my thoughtes</l>
               <l>Rapt with the thirſted action of my mind?</l>
               <l>O <hi>Clio, Honors Muſe,</hi> ſing in my voyce,</l>
               <l>Tell the attempt, and prophecie th'exploit</l>
               <l>Of his <hi>Eliza</hi>-conſecrated ſworde,</l>
               <l>That in this peacefull charme of <hi>Englands</hi> ſleepe,</l>
               <l>Opens moſt tenderlie her aged throte,</l>
               <l>Offring to poure freſh youth through all her vaines,</l>
               <l>That fleſh of braſſe, and ribs of ſteele retaines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Riches,</hi> and <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> and <hi>Renowme</hi> I ſing,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Riches</hi> with honour, <hi>Conqueſt</hi> without bloud,</l>
               <l>Enough to ſeat the Monarchie of earth,</l>
               <l>Like to <hi>Ioues</hi> Eagle, on <hi>Elizas</hi> hand.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Guiana,</hi> whoſe rich feet are mines of golde,</l>
               <l>Whoſe forehead knockes againſt the roofe of Starres,</l>
               <l>Stands on her tip-toes at faire <hi>England</hi> looking,</l>
               <l>Kiſſing her hand, bowing her mightie breast,</l>
               <l>And euery ſigne of all ſubmiſſion making,</l>
               <l>To be her ſiſter, and the daughter both</l>
               <l>Of our moſt ſacred Maide: whoſe barrenneſſe</l>
               <l>Is the true fruite of vertue, that may get,</l>
               <l>Beare and bring foorth anew in all perfection,</l>
               <l>What heretofore ſauage corruption held</l>
               <l>In barbarous <hi>Chaos;</hi> and in this affaire</l>
               <l>Become her father, mother, and her heire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then most admired Soueraigne, let your breath</l>
               <l>Goe foorth vpon the waters, and create</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9768:6"/>A golden worlde in this our yron age,</l>
               <l>And be the prosperous forewind to a Fleet,</l>
               <l>That ſeconding your last, may goe before it</l>
               <l>In all ſucceſſe of profite and renowme:</l>
               <l>Doubt not but your election was diuine,</l>
               <l>(Aſwell by <hi>Fate</hi> as your high iudgement ordred)</l>
               <l>To raiſe him with choiſe Bounties, that could adde</l>
               <l>Height to his height; and like a liberall vine,</l>
               <l>Not onelie beare his vertuous fruit aloft,</l>
               <l>Free from the Preſſe of ſquint-eyd <hi>Enuies</hi> feet,</l>
               <l>But decke his gracious Proppe with golden bunches,</l>
               <l>And ſhroude it with broad leaues of <hi>Rule</hi> oregrowne</l>
               <l>From all blacke tempeſtes of inuaſion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thoſe Conquests that like generall earthquakes ſhooke</l>
               <l>The ſolid world, and made it fall before them,</l>
               <l>Built all their braue attemptes on weaker groundes,</l>
               <l>And leſſe perſuaſiue likelihoods then this;</l>
               <l>Nor was there euer princelie Fount ſo long</l>
               <l>Powr'd foorth a ſea of Rule with ſo free courſe,</l>
               <l>And ſuch aſcending Maieſtie as you:</l>
               <l>Then be not like a rough and violent wind,</l>
               <l>That in the morning rends the Forreſtes downe,</l>
               <l>Shoues vp the ſeas to heauen, makes earth to tremble,</l>
               <l>And toombes his wastfull brauerie in the Euen:</l>
               <l>But as a riuer from a mountaine running,</l>
               <l>The further he extends, the greater growes,</l>
               <l>And by his thriftie race ſtrengthens his streame,</l>
               <l>Euen to ioyne battale with th'imperious ſea</l>
               <l>Diſdaining his repulſe, and in deſpight</l>
               <l>Of his proud furie, mixeth with his maine,</l>
               <l>Taking on him his titles and commandes:</l>
               <l>So let thy ſoueraigne Empire be encreast,</l>
               <l>And with <hi>Iberian Neptune</hi> part the stake,</l>
               <l>Whoſe <hi>Trident</hi> he the triple worlde would make.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9768:7"/>You then that would be wiſe in Wiſdomes ſpight,</l>
               <l>Directing with diſcredite of direction,</l>
               <l>And hunt for honour, hunting him to death.</l>
               <l>With whome before you will inherite gold,</l>
               <l>You will looſe golde, for which you looſe your ſoules;</l>
               <l>You that chooſe nought for right, but certaintie,</l>
               <l>And feare that value will get onlie blowes,</l>
               <l>Placing your faith in <hi>Incredulitie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sit till you ſee a woonder, <hi>Vertue</hi> rich:</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Honour</hi> hauing golde, rob golde of honour,</l>
               <l>Till as men hate deſert that getteth nought,</l>
               <l>They loath all getting that deſerues not ought;</l>
               <l>And vſe you gold-made men, as dregges of men;</l>
               <l>And till your poyſoned ſoules, like Spiders lurking</l>
               <l>In ſluttiſh chinckes, in mystes of Cobwebs hide</l>
               <l>Your foggie bodies, and your dunghill pride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O <hi>Incredulitie,</hi> the wit of Fooles,</l>
               <l>That ſlouenlie will spit on all thinges faire,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Cowards caſtle</hi> and the <hi>Sluggards cradle</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How eaſie t'is to be an Infidell?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But you <hi>Patrician</hi> Spirites that refine</l>
               <l>Your fleſh to fire, and iſſue like a flame</l>
               <l>On braue indeuours, knowing that in them</l>
               <l>The t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>act of heauen in morne-like glorie opens,</l>
               <l>That know you cannot be the Kinges of earth,</l>
               <l>(Claiming the Rightes of your creation)</l>
               <l>And let the Mynes of earth be Kinges of you;</l>
               <l>That are ſo farre from doubting likelie driftes,</l>
               <l>That in things hardest y'are most confident.</l>
               <l>You that know death liues, where power liues vnuſde,</l>
               <l>Ioying to ſhine in vvaues that burie you,</l>
               <l>And ſo make vvay for life euen through your graues;</l>
               <l>That vvill not be content like horſe to hold</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9768:7"/>A thread-bare beaten vvaie to home affaires:</l>
               <l>But where the ſea in enuie of your raigne,</l>
               <l>Cloſeth her vvombe, as fast as tis diſcloſde,</l>
               <l>That ſhe like <hi>Auarice</hi> might ſwallowe all,</l>
               <l>And let none find right paſſage through her rage:</l>
               <l>There your wiſe ſoules as ſwift as <hi>Eurus</hi> lead</l>
               <l>Your Bodies through, to profit and renowne,</l>
               <l>And skorne to let your bodies chooke your ſoules,</l>
               <l>In the rude breath and priſoned life of beastes:</l>
               <l>You that heerein renounce the courſe of earth,</l>
               <l>And lift your eies for guidance to the ſtarres,</l>
               <l>That liue not for your ſelues, but to poſſeſſe</l>
               <l>Your honour'd countrey of a generall ſtore;</l>
               <l>In pitie of the ſpoyle rude ſelfe-loue makes,</l>
               <l>Of them vvhoſe liues and yours one aire doth feede,</l>
               <l>One ſoile doeth nouriſh, and one ſtrength combine;</l>
               <l>You that are bleſt vvith ſence of all things noble</l>
               <l>In this attempt your compleat vvoorthes redouble.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But how is <hi>Nature</hi> at her heart corrupted,</l>
               <l>(<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> euen in her moſt ennobled birth?)</l>
               <l>How in exceſſe of Sence is Sence bereft her?</l>
               <l>That her moſt lightening-like effectes of luſt</l>
               <l>Wound through her fleſh, her ſoule, her fleſh vnwounded;</l>
               <l>And ſhe muſt neede incitements to her good,</l>
               <l>Euen from that part ſhe hurtes. O how moſt like</l>
               <l>Art thou (heroike Author of this Act)</l>
               <l>To this wrong'd ſoule of <hi>Nature</hi> that ſustainst</l>
               <l>Paine, charge, and perill for thy countreys good,</l>
               <l>And ſhe much like a bodie numb'd vvith ſurfets,</l>
               <l>Feeles not thy gentle applications</l>
               <l>For the health, vſe, &amp; honor of her powers.</l>
               <l>Yet ſhall my verſe through all her eaſe-lockt eares</l>
               <l>Trumpet the Nobleſſe of thy high intent,</l>
               <l>And if it cannot into act proceed,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9768:8"/>The fault and bitter pennance of the fault</l>
               <l>Make red ſome others eyes with penitence,</l>
               <l>For thine are cleare; and what more nimble ſpirites</l>
               <l>Apter to byte at ſuch vnhooked baytes,</l>
               <l>Gaine by our loſſe; that muſt we needs confeſſe</l>
               <l>Thy princelie valure would haue purchaſt vs.</l>
               <l>Which ſhall be fame eternall to thy name,</l>
               <l>Though thy contentment in thy graue deſires,</l>
               <l>Of our aduancement, faile deſeru'd effect,</l>
               <l>O how I feare thy glorie which I loue,</l>
               <l>Leaſt it ſhould dearelie growe by our decreaſe.</l>
               <l>Natures that ſtick in golden-graueld ſprings,</l>
               <l>In mucke-pits cannot ſcape their ſwallowings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But we ſhall foorth I know; Golde is our Fate,</l>
               <l>Which all our actes doeth faſhion and create.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then in the <hi>Theſpiads</hi> bright Propheticke Fount,</l>
               <l>Me thinkes I ſee our Liege riſe from her throne,</l>
               <l>Her eares and thoughtes in ſteepe amaze erected,</l>
               <l>At the moſt rare endeuour of her power.</l>
               <l>And now ſhe bleſſeth with her woonted Graces</l>
               <l>Th'induſtrious Knight, the ſoule of this exploit,</l>
               <l>Diſmiſſing him to conuoy of his ſtarres.</l>
               <l>And now for loue and honour of his woorth,</l>
               <l>Our twiſe-borne Nobles bring him Bridegroome-like,</l>
               <l>That is eſpouſde for vertue to his loue</l>
               <l>With feaſtes and muſicke, rauiſhing the aire,</l>
               <l>To his <hi>Argolian</hi> Fleet, where round about</l>
               <l>His bating Colours Engliſh valure ſwarmes</l>
               <l>In haste, as if <hi>Guianian Orenoque</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With his Fell waters fell vpon our ſhore.</l>
               <l>And now a wind as forward as their ſpirits,</l>
               <l>Sets their glad feet on ſmooth <hi>Guianas</hi> breaſt,</l>
               <l>Where (as if ech man were an <hi>Orpheus</hi>)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9768:8"/>A world of Sauadges fall came before them,</l>
               <l>Storing their theft-free treaſuries with golde,</l>
               <l>And there doth plentie crowne their wealthie fieldes,</l>
               <l>There <hi>Learning</hi> eates no more his thriftleſſe books,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Valure</hi> Estridge-like his yron armes.</l>
               <l>There <hi>Beautie</hi> is no ſtrumpet for her wantes,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Gallique</hi> humours putrifie her bloud:</l>
               <l>But all our Youth take <hi>Hymens</hi> lightes in hand,</l>
               <l>And fill each roofe with honor'd progenie.</l>
               <l>There makes <hi>Societie</hi> Adamantine chaines,</l>
               <l>And ioins their harts with wealth, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth diſioyn'd.</l>
               <l>There healthfull Recreations ſtrowe their meades,</l>
               <l>And make their manſions daunce with neighborhood,</l>
               <l>That here were drown'd in churliſh <hi>Auarice.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And there do Pallaces and temples riſe</l>
               <l>Out of the earth, and kiſſe th'enamored skies,</l>
               <l>Where new <hi>Britania,</hi> humblie kneeles to heauen,</l>
               <l>The world to her, and both at her bleſt feete,</l>
               <l>In whom the Circles of all Empire meet.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>G C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:9768:9"/>
            <head>Ad <hi>Thomam Hariotum</hi> Matheſeos, &amp; vniuerſae Philoſophiae peritiſsimum, de <hi>Guiana</hi> Carmen.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Dat. <date>Anno. 1595.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <l>MOntibus est Regio, quaſimuris, obſita, multis:</l>
            <l>Circumſaepit aquis quos Raleana ſuis.</l>
            <l>Intus habet largos Guaiana beata receſſus:</l>
            <l>hoſtili geſtans libera colla <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>go.</l>
            <l>Hiſpanus cliuis illis ſudauit, &amp; alſit</l>
            <l>ſeptem annos, nouies: nec tamen inualuit.</l>
            <l>(Numen, &amp; omen ineſt numeris. Fatale ſit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>i:</l>
            <l>Et nobis vertus ſit recidiua, precor)</l>
            <l>Gualtero, patefacta via eſt duce &amp; auſpice Ralegh</l>
            <l>Menſe vno: ô factum hoc nomine quo celebrem?</l>
            <l>Noctè die<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>, datis velis, remiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> laborans,</l>
            <l>Exegit ſummae dexteritatis opus.</l>
            <l>Scilicet expenſis magnis non ille pepercit,</l>
            <l>Communi natus conſuluiſſe bono.</l>
            <l>Prouidus excubuit ſimili diſcrimine Ioſeph:</l>
            <l>Sic fratres, fratrem deſeruêre ſuum:</l>
            <l>Fama coloratam deſignet ſi bona, vestem:</l>
            <l>Veſtis ſciſſa malis ſic fuit illa modis.</l>
            <l>Mira leges. Aureſque animumque tuum arrige. Tellus</l>
            <l>Haec aurum, &amp; gemmas graminis instar, habet.</l>
            <l>V'er ibi perpetuum eſt: ibi prodiga terra quotannis</l>
            <l>Luxuriat, ſola fertilitate nocens.</l>
            <l>Anglia noſtra licer diues ſit, &amp; vndique foelix:</l>
            <l>Anglia, ſi confers, indiga frugis erit.</l>
            <l>Expertes capitum, volucres, piſceſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> feraſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>
            </l>
            <l>Praetereo: haud proſunt, quae nouitate, placent.</l>
            <l>Eſt ibi, vel nuſquam, quod quaerimus. Ergo petamus:</l>
            <l>Det Deus, hanc Canaan poſſideamus. Amen.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tui Amantiſs. L. K.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9768:9"/>
            <head>The ſecond <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oyage <hi>to Guiana.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Vnday, the 26. of Ianuary, in the yeer of our Lord 1595 we depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Portland</hi> road, in the <hi>Darling</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> hauing in company the Diſcouerer, a ſmal Pynnace, whome wee loſt at ſea, in foule weather, the Thurſday night next following. Fryday, the 13. of Februarie, we fell with the <hi>Canarie</hi> Ilands, where we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected our pynnace, according to our appointment, ſeuen or eight dayes. Here we tooke two boats, the one a paſſenger, we bulged, the other wee towed at our ſhip ſterne, ſteering ſouth ſouth weſt for the Ilandes of <hi>Gap. de Verd.</hi> There hence we ſet ſaile the 28. of Februarie, keeping a weſt ſouth weſt courſe. In this paſſage we found verie ſmooth ſeas, faire weather, &amp; ſteddie winds, blowing ordinarilie between the Eaſt, and North eaſt pointes. Neere 300. leagues from theſe Ilands, we came into a growne ſea, the ſwollen waters ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſtrange noiſe and hurtling together, as if it might be two ſtrong currentes encountring each other. The 12. of March we ſounded, and had ſandie ground in 47. fadam. At midnight in twelue fadam we came to an ancor, the ground ſandie oaſe. Sunday the 14. towardes night, about ſome ſixe
<pb facs="tcp:9768:10"/>
leagues from the ſhoar, we deſcried a low land in the bottom of a bay. From the 9 of March vntill this time, wee kept for the moſt part a ſouth ſouth weſt courſe. The water in this place is ſmooth, but muddie, and the collour red or Tawny. From the weſtermoſt of the <hi>Cap. de Verd.</hi> Ilands vnto this bay I do eſtimat the diſtance to be neer 550. leagues. It ſemed to moſt of our ſea-men to be the verie banke of a ſhoald vpon a leigh ſhoare: the rather becauſe without it, in the cleane greene ſea we had but 7. fadam depth: but after by proofe finding that there is no ſudden alteration in anie part of the coaſt and that the ſea is ſmootheſt nere the land, we alwaies at night ſought to ancor in three or four fadam. And doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe as the hand of God is woonderfull in all his workes: ſo heerin his mercifull prouidence is moſt admirable, that vpon a leigh ſhore, ſubiect to a perpetuall eaſterlie g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, neither much wind can endanger ſhipping by reaſon that the foule heauie water is not capable of vehement motion, and the ſofte light oaſe, if they touch, cannot bruiſe them: nor is there anie ieopardie in being wind-bound or imbayed: for the moſt forcible windes make the greateſt floud-tydes, whereby the freſhets, when they take their ordinarie courſe of ebbe, doe grow ſtrong and ſwift, ſetting directlie off to ſea againſt the wind. We by turning went cleare of all bayes: howbeit in this caſe, as alſo in the riuers, the vſe of a droue ſayle ſeemeth a good and readie help. The firſt place wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ancored, was in the mouth of <hi>Arrowa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> a faire &amp; great riuer. It ſtandeth in one degree and fourtie minutes: for we fell ſo farre to the ſouthwards by your Lordſhips dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. The bar without hath at the leaſt three fadam, at the ſholdeſt place, when it is low ebb The depth within is eight and ten fadam. The water alwayes brackiſh. We found not anie inhabitantes in this place neere the ſea coaſt. I omit here to recite the names of the nations that are borderers, their townes, Captaines and commodities that their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries doe yeelde, as alſo the ſoundinges, tydes, and how the
<pb facs="tcp:9768:10"/>
coaſt lyeth &amp;c. thinking it fitteſt to reduce theſe diſioyned and ſcattered remembrances to one place. As we paſſed we alwaies kept the ſhoare within view and ſtopped the flouds, ſtill ancoring at night in three or foure fadam. When wee came to the north-hed la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of this bay (which we named <hi>Cape Cecyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) we ſawe two high mountaines like two Ilandes but they ioyne with the mayne. In this tract lying north north-weſt neere 60. leagues, there fall into the ſea, theſe ſeuerall great riuers <hi>Arrowari, Iwaripoco, Maipari, Coanawini, Caipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogh.</hi> We ancored in two fadam not far from theſe hilles and filled all our caske with freſh water by the ſhip ſide for in the ſea 30. miles from the mouth of anie riuer it is freſh and good This ſecond bay extendeth it ſelfe aboue 30. leagues to the weſtward, &amp; containeth within it theſe riuers <hi>Arcooa, Wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>apoco, wanari, Caparwacka, Cawo, Carare, wia, Macuria Cawroor Curaſſawini.</hi> Here leauing the ſhip at ancor, I tooke into the boat <hi>Iohn Prouost,</hi> my <hi>Indian</hi> Interpreter, <hi>Iohn Lynſer,</hi> and 8. or nine others, intending to ſearch ſome of theſe riuers, and to ſeeke ſpeech with the <hi>Indians.</hi> In <hi>Wiapoco</hi> at the foot of the Eaſtermoſt mountaine, where the riuer falleth into the ſea, we found twentie or thirtie houſes, but not inhabited. Wee ſtayed there but one night. <hi>Wanari</hi> we ouerpaſſed, becauſe the entrance is rockie and not deep. In <hi>Capperwacka</hi> we ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſome fourtie miles but could ſee no <hi>Indian.</hi> At one of their portes vnder the ſide of a hill, we took in ſo much Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill wood as our boat could carie. Amongſt other trees wee cut downe one for an example, which I doe verilie beleeue to bee the ſame ſorte of Sinamon, which is founde in the ſtreightes of <hi>Magellane.</hi> From <hi>Capurwacka</hi> wee paſſed to <hi>Cawo,</hi> and there met with a <hi>Canoa,</hi> wherein were two <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> It was long time before we could procure them to come neere vs, for they doubted leaſt we were Spaniſh. When my interpreter had perſwaded them the contrarie, and that wee came from <hi>England,</hi> they without farther ſpeech or delay, brought vs to <hi>Wareo</hi> their Captaine, who entertained vs
<pb facs="tcp:9768:11"/>
moſt frendly: and then at large declared vnto vs, that he was latelie chaſed by the <hi>Spaniard</hi> from <hi>Moruga,</hi> one of the neighbour riuers to <hi>Raleana,</hi> or <hi>Orenoque:</hi> and that hauing burnt his owne houſes, and deſtroyed his fruites and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, he had left his countrey and townes to be poſſeſſed by the <hi>Arwaccas;</hi> who are a vagabound nation of <hi>Indians,</hi> which finding no certaine place of abode of their owne, do for the moſt part ſerue and follow the <hi>Spaniardes.</hi> He ſhewed mee that he was of the nation of the <hi>Iaos,</hi> who are a mightie peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and of late time were Lordes of all the ſea coaſt ſo farre as <hi>Trinidado,</hi> which they likewiſe poſſeſſed. Howbeit, that with a generall conſent, when the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> firſt began to borrow ſome of their wiues: they all agreed to change their habitation, &amp; doe now liue vnited for the moſt part towards the riuer of <hi>Amazones.</hi> But the eſpeciall cauſe of his preſent remooue was, becauſe two or three yeares paſt, twenty <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niardes</hi> came to his towne, and ſought to take his beſt wife from him: but before they caried her away, hee at time and place of aduantage killed halfe of them: the reſt fled, moſt of them ſore hurt. Now in this caſe he thought it beſt to dwel far ynough from them. Your <hi>Indian</hi> Pilot <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> who conducted you by <hi>Amana,</hi> and now abideth neere the head of <hi>Deſſekeebe,</hi> is one of this mans ſubiects: By whom (as it may ſeeme) hee hath taken good notice of our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and country. For he deſcended more particularlie to inquire what forces were come with vs, aſſuring me of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> being in <hi>Trinidado,</hi> and that the <hi>Indians</hi> our friends betwixt hope and feare, haue earneſtlie expected our return from <hi>England</hi> theſe foure or fiue moneths. When I had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him, that at our departure we left no <hi>Spaniards</hi> aliue to annoy them; that we now came onlie to diſcouer, &amp; trade with them; and that if her Maieſtie ſhould haue ſent a power of men, where no enemie was to reſiſt, the <hi>Indians</hi> might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps imagine, that we came rather to inuade, then to defend them. He replyed, that this courſe very well ſorted with the
<pb facs="tcp:9768:11"/>
report, which they had heard of our Princeſſe Iuſtice, rare graces, &amp; vertues: the fame of whoſe power in being able to vanquiſh the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and ſingular goodneſſe in vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to ſuccour and defend the afflicted <hi>Indians,</hi> was now ſo generall that the nations farre and neere were all agreed to ioyne with vs and by all meanes poſsible to aſsiſt vs in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling and rooting out the <hi>Spaniards</hi> from all partes of the land: and that we were deceiued, if we thought this country not large ynough to receiue vs, without moleſtation or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion vpon the <hi>Indians,</hi> who wanted not choiſe of dwelling places, if they forſooke one to liue in another: but ſtood in neede of our preſence at all times to aide them, and maintaine their libertie, which to them is dearer then land or liuing. He then farther deſired, that hee with his people might haue our fauour againſt the <hi>Arwaccas,</hi> who not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing content to enioy their groundes and houſes, had taken from them manie of their wiues and children, the beſt of whoſe fortune was, if they liued, to liue in perpetuall ſlauerie vnder the <hi>Spaniardes.</hi> Wee put him in good hope and comfort thereof. And he to deſerue ſome part of this friendſhip, commended vnto vs an elderlie man to bee our Pilot in bringing vs to <hi>Raleana.</hi> When we were readie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part,<note place="margin">Braſil wood</note> he demanded whether we wanted any <hi>Vrapo</hi> which is the wood, that is vſually carried from theſe partes to <hi>Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dado</hi> in <hi>Canoas,</hi> and is there ſolde to the <hi>French</hi> for trade: he offered, if we would bring our ſhip neer his Port; to put in her lading thereof. But becauſe moſt of our caske was not yron bound, and in making ſtoage way to remooue it, would haue bene the loſſe of our Syder and other drinke; I therefore referred the taking of any quantity to fitter op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie: thinking it ſufficient at this time, to haue only my boates lading therof: which afterwardes in extremity of foule weather before we could get aboord our ſhippe, wee were inforced in a dark nigh to heaue al ouerbord: thinking our ſelues happy, to haue recouered thither at ſeuen dayes
<pb facs="tcp:9768:12"/>
end, with ſafety of lyfe onlie. All which time wee could no where ſet foot on ſhore, but reſted day and night wet &amp; wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beaten in our couertles boat which was ſometimes rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to ſinke vnder vs. For we had in this place without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon more raine, wind, and guſtes then els where at anie time. To be breefe, my men became weake and ſicke, and if we had ſtayed anie longer time out, I doubt whether the greateſt part of vs had euer come abord again. I afterwards vnderſtood by my <hi>Indian</hi> Pilot, that this weather is for moſt part of the yeare vſuall neere the Iland <hi>Oncaiarie,</hi> which ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth North from the riuer <hi>Capurwacka</hi> ſome ſixe leagues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſea: and that they hold opinion this Iland to be kept by ſome euill ſpirit: for they verily beleeue, that to ſleepe in the day time neere it (except it be after much drinke) is preſent death. The onely ſeaſon wherein little raine doth fall there, is (as I gathered by their ſpeach they diuiding all times by their moones) at our winter Solſtice. The mother winde of this coaſt is for the moſt part to the Northwarde of the Eaſt, except when the Sunne is on this ſide of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall, for then it often yeares Southerly, but moſt in the night. This our guide is of the <hi>Iaos,</hi> who doe all marke themſelues, thereby to be knowne from other nations af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this maner. With the tooth of a ſmall beaſt like a Rat, they race ſome their faces, ſome their bodies, after diuers formes, as if it were with the ſcratch of a pin, the print of which raſure, can neuer be done away againe during lyfe. When he had ſome time conuerſed with our <hi>Indians,</hi> that went from <hi>England</hi> with vs he became willing of himſelfe to ſee our country. His ſufficiency, truſtines, &amp; knowledge is ſuch, that if the prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded voyage for the <hi>Guiana</hi> do take place, you ſhall (I doubt not) find him many wayes able to ſteed your Lordſh. in your deſignes &amp; purpoſes. For beſides his preciſe knowledge of all the coaſt, of the <hi>Indian</hi> townes and dwellings, he ſpeaketh all their languages, was bred in <hi>Guiana,</hi> is a ſworne brother to <hi>Putima,</hi> who ſlew the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9768:12"/>
in their returne from <hi>Manoa,</hi> can direct vs to many Golde mines and in nothing will vndertake more, then he aſſuredlie will performe.</p>
            <p>To the Weſtward this bay hath many good roades vnder ſmall Ilandes, whereof the greateſt, named <hi>Gowateri,</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited by the <hi>Shebatos:</hi> and beſides the plentie of foule, fiſh fruites wilde Porkes and Deere, which are there to bee had: where <hi>Caiane</hi> falles into the ſea, (for it ſtandeth in the mouthes of <hi>Wia</hi> and <hi>Caiane</hi>) it yeeldes ſaie and good har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in foure and fiue fadam for ſhips of great burthen. On all that coaſt we found not any like it: we therfore honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this place by the name of <hi>Port Howard.</hi> The road vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Triangle</hi> Ilands; which are the Weſtermoſt from the reſt and ſtand in 5. degrees which haue alſo ſtore of fiſh foule, Deere and <hi>Iwanas</hi> is good, but not comparable with this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, where in all windes and weather ſhippes though they be manie, may all ride ſecurelie. The hils and high lands are limits to this bay on each ſide: for to the Eaſtward beyond it appeare none at all, and to the Weſtward of Mount <hi>Hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beïgh</hi> very few. Where the mountaines faile, there Braſill wood is no farther to be ſought for: but in all partes cotten, pepper, ſilke, and <hi>Balſamum</hi> trees do grow in aboundance. The rootes of the herbe <hi>Wiapaſſa</hi> are here moſt plentifull: I find them in taſte nothing different from good Ginger, &amp; in operation verie medicinable againſt the flixe and head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach. Theſe riuers, as alſo others neerer <hi>Raleana,</hi> do al fal out of the plaines of the Empire ouer rockes, as the riuer <hi>Caroli</hi> doeth into <hi>Raleana:</hi> and in moſt places within the vtmoſt hedge of woods, the land within is plaine, voyd of trees; and beareth ſhort graſſe like <hi>Arromaiaries</hi> country.</p>
            <p>Next adioyning vnto theſe, are the riuers <hi>Cunanamma, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>racco, Mawari, Mawarparo, Amonna, Marawini, Oncowi, Wiawiami, Aramatappo, Camaiwini, Shurinama, Shurama, Cupanamma, Inana, Curitini, Winitwari, Berbice, Wapari, Maicaiwini, Mahawaica, Wappari, Lemerare, Deſſekebe, Caopui,
<pb facs="tcp:9768:13"/>
Pawrooma, Moruga, Waini, Barima, Amacur, Aratoori, Rale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana.</hi> From <hi>Cape Cecyll</hi> to <hi>Raleana,</hi> the coaſt trendeth 200. leagues next hande Weſt north weſt. In this variety of goodly riuers, <hi>Amonna</hi> amongſt the reſt poureth himſelfe into the ſea in a large and deepe channel: his ſwiftnes ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth no barre, nor refuſeth any ſhipping of what burthen ſoeuer they be: within his mouth for good and hopefull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectes is port <hi>Burley</hi> placed. The inhabitants that dwell Eaſtward, doe neuer paſſe lower then <hi>Berbice</hi> to trade. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue <hi>Curitini</hi> in the woods they gather great quantities of honey. Farther to the Eaſtward then <hi>Deſſekebe,</hi> no <hi>Spaniard</hi> euer trauelled. In which reſpect, and that no ſea-card that I haue ſeene at anie time, doth in any ſort neere a truth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe this coaſt: I thought the libertie of impoſing Engliſh names to certaine places of note, of right to belong vnto our labours; the rather becauſe occaſion thereby offereth it ſelfe, gratefullie to acknowledge the honor due vnto them that haue bene, and I hope will ſtill continue, fauourers of this enterprize. The <hi>Indians</hi> to ſhew the worthines of <hi>Deſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keebe</hi> (for it is verie large and full of Ilands in the mouth) do call it the brother of <hi>Orenoque.</hi> It lyeth Southerly into the land, and from the mouth of it vnto the head, they paſſe in twentie dayes: then taking their prouiſion they carie it on their ſhoulders one dayes iourney: afterwards they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne for their Canoas, and beare them likwiſe to the ſide of a lake, which the <hi>Iaos</hi> call <hi>Roponowini,</hi> the <hi>Charibes, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rime:</hi> which is of ſuch bigneſſe, that they know no difference between it and the maine ſea. There be infinite numbers of Canoas in this lake, and (as I ſuppoſe) it is no other then that, whereon <hi>Manoa</hi> ſtandeth: In this riuer, which wee now call <hi>Deuoritia,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> doe intend to build them a towne. In <hi>Moruga</hi> it was, that they hunted <hi>Wareo</hi> and his people,<note place="margin">In Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</note> about halfe a yeere ſince. <hi>Arromaiarie,</hi> who wan ſo great credit by ouerthrowing the <hi>Tiuitiuas</hi> of <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and making free the paſſage of that riuer, but now againe
<pb facs="tcp:9768:13"/>
liueth in diſgrace, by reaſon that the <hi>Charibes</hi> of <hi>Guanipa,</hi> haue killed moſt of his followers, and burnt his townes, was preſent with them, and tooke away manie of the women of that place. <hi>Arracurri,</hi> another <hi>Indian</hi> of the nation of the <hi>Arwaccas</hi> inhabiting in <hi>Barima,</hi> was likewiſe preſent, and conducted the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to all the <hi>Indian</hi> dwellings. They were not of <hi>Anthonie de Berreo</hi> his companie, that followed this chaſe, but were the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> of <hi>Marguerita,</hi>
               <note place="margin">This Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth the Guiana lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and is reputed a very ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent man.</note> and the <hi>Caraccas,</hi> with whom <hi>Santiago,</hi> forſaking his gouernor <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reo,</hi> ioyned himſelfe. For which fact he now lyeth in fetters at <hi>Trinidado,</hi> euery day expecting ſentence of death. The occaſion hereof grew as followeth.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Berreo,</hi> hauing loſt his men, was left with <hi>Faſſhardo</hi> at <hi>Cumanaw</hi> all alone, as forlorne, and neuer likely to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe his intended conqueſt of <hi>Guiana:</hi> the Gouernours of the <hi>Caraccas</hi> and <hi>Marguerita</hi> conſulting together, ſent with all ſpeed into <hi>Spaine,</hi> to aduertiſe their king, that <hi>Berreo</hi> was vtterly vnable to follow this enterpriſe, that he had giuen it ouer, and did now ſoiorne in his olde dayes at <hi>Faſſhardo</hi> his houſe, minding nothing els but his ſolace, and recreation. they farther declared, of how great importance this matter was: and that an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman of ſuch reckoning, as they named your Lordſhip to be, hauing bene in the <hi>Guia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and vnderſtanding ſo much of the ſtate thereof, and the nations thereunto adioyning, as <hi>Topiawarie,</hi> being both olde and wiſe, could informe you of, who alſo in confirmation of friendſhip, had giuen you his only ſonne, to whome the inheritance of the countrey did belong after him: there was no other likelihood, but that you, who aduentured ſo farre, and in ſuch ſort as you did, only to ſee, and know a certen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, would leaue nothing vnattempted to poſſeſſe ſo rich a countrie, and without all doubt would returne preſentlie. That meane time, you had left this aged Sire aliue, to bee a blocke in their way, to whome after his deceaſe, this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe by patent did belong, and to be a weake aduerſarie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:9768:14"/>
your ſelf, whom at all times, you knew eaſilie how to diſtreſſe: and that therefore it might bee behoouefull for his maieſtie to reuoke <hi>Berreo</hi> his graunt, and to vſe their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, who were readie and willing without anie delay to vndertake the charge. Theſe newes being at large amplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and deliuered to the king: <hi>Domingo de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>era, Bereo</hi> his Camp. maſter, who was ſent into <hi>Spaine,</hi> fiue monethes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your arriual to <hi>Trinidado,</hi> with a ſufficient quantitie of golde, gotten out of <hi>Guiana,</hi> to leuie and furniſh 500. men, hauing gotten knowledge of this practiſe ſo ſollicited this cauſe in <hi>Bereo</hi> his behalfe, that preſent order was giuen for the victualing and manning of ten ſhips to bee ſent to <hi>Bereo:</hi> and farther, this golde bore ſuch waight, that the king commanded other 18. of his ſhips to ſtop at <hi>Trinida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> and not to follow their other directions, before they ſaw that place ſecured from enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Berreo</hi> ſuppoſing that theſe Gouernours in ſending with ſuch ſpeed into <hi>Spaine,</hi> meant him no good: to approoue his care and conſtancie, &amp; that he neuer would yeeld vnder the burthen of his aduerſe fortune; giuing no time or breath to his aduerſaries, nor himſelf; returned forthwith to <hi>Carapana</hi> his port, onlie with fifteene men, being the ſcattered rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of thoſe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you lately diſpoſſeſſed of <hi>Trinidado.</hi> Theſe Gouernours followed him, and aſſuring themſelues of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent imployment from their king, preoccupating the time of their directions to be returned from <hi>Spaine,</hi> entered the <hi>Guiana</hi> with their men, with full determination to murther <hi>Bereo,</hi> and to diſpatch all his companie. They indeed killed two or three, but <hi>Bereo</hi> fled towards <hi>Caroli,</hi> where he ſtayed hoping for ſuccour from his ſonne <hi>Anthonie de Cemenes,</hi> to come downe the riuer from <hi>Nueuo Reyno de Granado.</hi> The <hi>Margueritanes</hi> with their accomplices buſied themſelues, ſome in ſearching the countrie, others in purueying of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals out of the riuers that doe lie Eaſtward, of which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber theſe were, that entered into <hi>Moruga</hi> with 20. <hi>Canoas.
<pb facs="tcp:9768:14"/>
Santiago</hi> paſſed vp into <hi>Topiawaries</hi> countrie, and there tooke <hi>Francis Sparrowes</hi> Sir <hi>George Gifford</hi> his man priſoner, who with plentie of golde ranſomed his life, and is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding in <hi>Cumanaw.</hi> This done, they all returned to <hi>Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dado,</hi> and began to build their towne there, when vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happilie to their ſmall comfort the 28. ſayles arriued, and tooke <hi>Santiago</hi> priſoner. The other Actors in this Enterlude vaniſhed, and in <hi>Canoas</hi> recouered <hi>Marguerita</hi> and <hi>Cuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naw</hi> againe. Eighteen of the ſaid ſhips leauing all thinges in good order, departed from <hi>Trinidado</hi> to follow their other directions: ten doe yet remaine fortifying at <hi>Conquerabia,</hi> and expecting our comming.</p>
            <p>This particular relation I had from an <hi>Indian,</hi> ſeruant to <hi>Berreo,</hi> that could ſpeake Spaniſh, whom I tooke in the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. He is of the nation of the <hi>Iaos,</hi> and from a child bred vp with <hi>Berreo.</hi> I gaue him trade to buy him a <hi>Canoa</hi> to returne into his countrie, and ſo left him glad, that hee had met with vs.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Indians</hi> of <hi>Moruga</hi> being chaſed from their dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, do ſeeke by all means poſsible, to accorde all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in one, ſo to inuade the <hi>Arwaccas,</hi> who were guides to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in ſhewing their townes, and betraying them. For they are fullie perſwaded, that by driuing theſe <hi>Arwac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas,</hi> who ſerue the <hi>Spaniards</hi> (for a great parte of this nation doth alſo hate, or not know them) out of their territories, and <hi>Trinidado,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> for want of bread, will be infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſeeke habitation farther of, or at the leaſt in time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume and be waſted.</p>
            <p>The 6. day of Aprill wee came to an ancor within the mouth of the riuer <hi>Raleana,</hi> hauing ſpent twentie and three dayes in diſcouerie vpon this coaſt. The channell of this ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath ſixe or ſeuen fadam depth, nine or ten miles off at ſea, the barre lyeth farther out, and at low water hath not full two fadam. It highes not aboue fiue foote, except at a ſpring tyde. We ancored in ten fadam the firſt night: the
<pb facs="tcp:9768:15"/>
next morning twelue <hi>Canoas</hi> came vnto vs, furniſhed &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided of victualles after their manner for the warres. Their Captaines names were <hi>Anawra,</hi> and <hi>Aparwa.</hi> Theſe <hi>Caſſiques</hi> when the Spaniards made the laſt inrode in thoſe parts, were in the Inland amongſt the <hi>Iwarewakerie</hi> their neighbors, by which occaſion hauing loſt ſome of their wiues (for notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their profeſsion of Chriſtianitie, ſome of theſe Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards keep ten or twelue women, thinking themſelues wel and ſurelie bleſſed, howſoeuer they liue, if their towne and houſes be religiouſlie croſſed) they kept together thirtie <hi>Canoas,</hi> hoping at our comming, which they had now long expected to recouer this loſſe vpon them, and the <hi>Arwaccas</hi> who in their abſence had done this wrong. They ſhewed me this their purpoſe, and required to be ioyned in league of friendſhip with vs againſt our enemies. When of them I had learned ſo much of the preſent eſtate of the country, as they did know: they demanded whether we had brought no more forces with vs, but onely one ſhip? I anſwered them as before I did the others, that we now came onlie to trade, not knowing vntil this preſent that any Spaniards wer in the <hi>Guiana;</hi> that vpon our returne our whole Fleete will ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to ſet forwards, and that in the meane time, we woulde now viſite our friends and help them ſo farre as we could in anie thing, that we ſhould finde needfull preſently to be done. After long diſcourſe (for their chief man ſtayed with me all night) when hee had cauſed mee to ſpit in my right hand, with manie other ceremonies which they vſe in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming friendſhip, he went to the ſhoare, and one of his <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noas</hi> he ſent to bring forwards the other twentie: one other he cauſed to go vp the riuer before vs, to bring intelligence. Then calling together the cheif of his companie, they made ſmall fyers, and ſitting in their <hi>Hamaccas,</hi> each one ſorted himſelf with a companion, recounting amongſt themſelues the worthieſt deeds, and deathes of their Anceſtors, execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their enemies moſt deſpightfullie, &amp; magnifying their
<pb facs="tcp:9768:15"/>
friendes with all titles of praiſes and honour, that may bee deuiſed. Thus they ſit talking, and taking <hi>Tobacco</hi> ſome two howers, and vntill their pipes bee all ſpent (for by them they meaſure the time of this their ſolemne conference) no man muſt interrupt, or diſturbe them in anie ſorte: for this is their religion, and prayers, which they nowe celebrated, keeping a preciſe faſt one whole day in honour of the great Princeſſe of the North, their Patroneſſe &amp; Defender.<note place="margin">Her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.</note> Their <hi>Canoas</hi> being made readie, they accompanied vs, and in the way ſhewed vs, where the ſhoalds of the riuer doe lie. By this Captaine I learned that <hi>Muchikeri</hi> is the name of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie where <hi>Macureguerai</hi> the firſt towne of the Empire of <hi>Guiana,</hi> that lyeth towardes <hi>Raieana,</hi> is ſeated in a faire and exceeding large plaine, belowe the high mountaines that beare Northweſterly from it, that it is but three dayes ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney diſtant from <hi>Carapana</hi> his porte: and that <hi>Monoa</hi> is but ſixe daies farther. That they themſelues doe paſſe in three dayes into the countrie of the <hi>Iwarewakeries</hi> by the riuer <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macur,</hi> which though it be not the directeſt, yet is it the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt way to <hi>Macureguerai</hi> for that which leadeth by <hi>Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pana</hi> his dwelling, is in ſome places difficult, and mountey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous. That a nation of clothed people, called <hi>Caſſanari,</hi> doe dwell not far from the place, where the riuer doth firſt take the name of <hi>Orenoque,</hi> and that farre within, they border vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſea of ſalt water, named <hi>Parime.</hi> That a great riuer, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Macurwini,</hi> paſſeth through their countrie into <hi>Oreno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que.</hi> That <hi>Manoa</hi> ſtandeth twentie dayes iourney from the mouth of <hi>Wiapoco:</hi> ſixteene dayes from <hi>Barima:</hi> thirteene dayes from <hi>Amacur,</hi> and ten dayes from <hi>Aratoori.</hi> That the beſt way vnto it, is not by <hi>Macureguerai,</hi> becauſe it is in ſome places comberſome and rockie. That of all others the <hi>Charibes</hi> that dwell high vp in <hi>Orenoque,</hi> knowe moſt of the inland, and of thoſe nations, &amp; that they ſpeak no other lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, then ſuch as <hi>Iohn</hi> your Interpreter doth well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. He certified me of the headleſſe men, and that their
<pb facs="tcp:9768:16"/>
mouthes in their breaſts are exceeding wide. The name of their nation in the <hi>Charibes</hi> language <hi>Chiparemai,</hi>
               <note place="margin">They haue eminent heads like dogs, &amp; liue all day time in the ſea they ſpeake the Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage.</note> and the <hi>Guianians</hi> call them <hi>Ewiapanomos.</hi> What I haue heard of a ſorte of people more monſtrous, I omit to mention, becauſe it is no matter of difficultie to get one of them, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port otherwiſe will appear fabulous. Laſtlie, he told me of an Inland riuer, named <hi>Cawrooma,</hi> adioyning to <hi>Aratoori,</hi> and that the <hi>Cuepyn</hi> mountaines, where <hi>Carapana</hi> dwelleth, are hardlie acceſsible. That the <hi>Amapagotos</hi> haue images of gold of incredible bigneſſe, and greate ſtore of vnmanned horſes of the <hi>Carackas</hi> breed: and that they dwell fiue dayes iourny vp the riuer about <hi>Caroli.</hi> We with our fleet of <hi>Canoas</hi> were now not farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Carapanas</hi> port, when our intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer returned &amp; informed vs that ten Spaniardes were lately gone with much trade to <hi>Barima,</hi> wher theſe Indians dwelt, to buy <hi>Caſſaua</hi> bread: and that within one day two other <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noas</hi> of Spaniards were appointed to come by the riuer <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana,</hi> to <hi>Carapana</hi> his porte. Vpon this occaſion they took counſell, and in the end deſired to returne to their houſes, leaſt the Spaniards finding them from home, and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that they did purpoſelie abſent themſelues, ſhould take away their wiues, and ſpoile their dwellings. They farther reſolued, if it were poſsible to cut them off. Which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they did performe. For when they were diſperſed in their houſes ſeeking <hi>Caſſaua:</hi> ſuddenlie at one time, in all places they were aſſaulted, and not one of them eſcaped. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rapana,</hi> whoſe hande was in laying this plot, ſent vs this newes, as we returned downe the riuer. The two other <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noas</hi> that came from <hi>Trinidado</hi> by <hi>Amana,</hi> notwithſtanding that we kept a league before the ſhip with our boates, ſawe the ſhip before we had ſight of them, and preſentlie with all ſpeed went to <hi>Berreo</hi> to aduertiſe him of our comming. He foorthwith diſpatched two or three meſſengers to <hi>Trinida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do.</hi> One of his <hi>Canoas</hi> met with our Spie, whome the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of <hi>Barima</hi> had left to goe with vs: they rifled him of his
<pb facs="tcp:9768:16"/>
victuals, gaue him kniues, and diſmiſſed him,</p>
            <p>In 8. dayes ſayling ſtill before a wind, we arriued at <hi>Topi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awaries</hi> porte, in all which time, no Indian that wee knewe came aboord vs. For the time of our returne promiſed at your Lordſhips departure from thence, being expired; they in diſpair ſeuered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues amongſt the other nations. Here the Spaniards haue ſeated their <hi>Rarceria</hi> of ſome twentie or thirtie houſes. The high rockie Ilande, that lyeth in the middeſt of the riuer, againſt the mouth of <hi>Caroli,</hi> is their fort or refuge, when they miſdoubt ſafetie in their town, or haue notice of any practiſe againſt them: but nowe leauing both towne and Iland, they ioyned themſelues altogether, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring to the mouth of the riuer <hi>Caroli,</hi> placed there a ſecret ambuſh, to defend the paſſage to thoſe mines, from whence your Oare and white ſtones were taken the laſt yeare: Wee all not without griefe to ſee our ſelues thus defeated, &amp; our hungrie hopes made voide, were witneſſes of this their remooue. As we road at an ancor within musket ſhot of their towne, an Indian came vnto vs with leane cheekes, thinne haire, and a ſquint eye, to informe vs that they were verie ſtrong, that <hi>Berreo</hi> his ſon was with him, that they had but two ſmall Pynnaces at <hi>Trinidado,</hi> which they daylie looked for to come vp the riuer, and laſtlie to view our ſhip wel, and our prouiſion, but eſpeciallie to learne whether <hi>Gualtero, To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piawarie</hi> his ſonne were with vs.</p>
            <p>This Informers verie countenance gaue him to bee ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and therefore partlie by threatning, partlie by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of reward we won him to confeſſe the trueth. Which he did, aſſuring vs that <hi>Berreo</hi> had not full 55. men with him, whereof twentie came lately from <hi>Trinidado:</hi> twentie from <hi>Nueuo Reyno,</hi> and the reſt hee brougt with him about ſixe moneths ſince, when he fled from <hi>Carapana</hi> his port, &amp; was driuen with his ſmall companie to keepe the foreſaid Iland neer <hi>Caroli.</hi> And that though now his number is thus increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet dareth he not aduenture at any time to leaue the faſt
<pb facs="tcp:9768:17"/>
woods, and to goe but halfe a league from his holde into the plains. That ſome few of the <hi>Arwaccas</hi> are abiding with him That he dailie looketh for his ſonne from <hi>Nueuo Reyno,</hi> for his Campemaiſter from <hi>Trinidado,</hi> and for horſes from the <hi>Caraccas.</hi> That <hi>Topiawarie</hi> is dead: the Indians of that coaſt all fled, and diſperſed, excepting the ſonne of one <hi>Curmatoi,</hi> and another woman of account, whom the Spaniards hold priſoners, for conſenting to the death of their nine men, &amp; the holie Frier in <hi>Morekito</hi> his time. This <hi>Curmatoi</hi> is fled towards <hi>Guanipa,</hi> and is a man of ſpeciall note amongſt the Indians. That <hi>Iwiakanarie</hi>
               <note place="margin">Topiawarie his ſonne.</note> 
               <hi>Gualtero</hi> his neere kinſman, hath held the country to his vſe, by his fathers appointment, euer ſince your being in the riuer. That there are ten ſhippes, and, manie Spaniards at <hi>Trinidado.</hi> That the Indians our friendes did feare, leaſt you with your companie were all ſlaine, and your ſhips ſunke at <hi>Cumanaw</hi> (for ſo the Spaniards noyſed it amongſt them.) that ſome of <hi>Gualtero</hi> his frinds with <hi>Putij<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> were in the mountaines not farre from the hill <hi>Aio.</hi> And that <hi>Berreo</hi> had ſent for ſixe peeces of ordinance, which hee meant to plante, where they might beſt commaund the riuer.</p>
            <p>When we had ſtayed here two dayes, conſidering that where no hope was left of doing good: to abide there in harmes way doing nothing, would be bootleſſe: I reſolued to ſeek <hi>Putijma</hi> in the mounteines: and turning downe the riuer with the force of the ſtreame ſome twentie miles in ſixe houres: the next morning with tenne ſhot I went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore, intending if the <hi>Indians</hi> ſhould thinke themſelues too weake, with our helpe to diſplant the Spaniardes: to ſet ſome of them on worke, for hatchets and kniues to returne vs gold graines, and white ſtones from ſuch places, as they ſhould be directed vnto. When we came to the place of their vſuall abode: we ſawe that they latelie had bene there, but could ſpeake with none of them. It may be that feare (which is eaſie of beleefe) perſwaded them that wee were Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,
<pb facs="tcp:9768:17"/>
               <hi>Gilbert</hi> my Pylot, here offered to bring vs eyther to the myne of white ſtones neere <hi>Winicapora,</hi> or els to a golde myne, which <hi>Putijma</hi> had ſhewed him, being but one dayes iourney ouer land, from the place where we now ſtayed at an ancor. I ſawe farre off the mountaine adioyning to this golde mine and hauing meaſured their paths nere the ſame place this laſt yeare, could not iudge it to bee fit eene miles from vs. I doe well remember how comming that way with <hi>Putijma</hi> the yeare before, he pointed to this ſame mountain making ſigns to haue me go with him thither. I vnderſtood his ſignes, and marked the place, but miſtooke his meaning, imagining that he would haue ſhewed mee the ouerfall of the riuer <hi>Curwara</hi> from the mountains. My <hi>Indian</hi> ſhewed me in what ſort without diging they gather the gold in the ſand of a ſmall riuer, name <hi>Macawini,</hi> that ſpringeth and falleth from the rocks, where this mine is. And farther told me, that he was with <hi>Putijma,</hi> at what time <hi>Morekito</hi> was to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> &amp; that then the cheif of <hi>Morekito</hi> his friends were in conſultation, to ſhew this mine vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if ſo they might redeem their Captains life; but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> better aduiſe, ſuppoſing them in this caſe to bee implacable, and that this might prooue a means to looſe not only their king, but their country alſo: they haue to this day concealed it from them, being of all others the richeſt, and moſt plentifull The a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſort, to keep this from common knowledge, haue deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a fable of a dangerous Dragon that haunteth this place and deuoureth all that come neer it. But our <hi>Indian,</hi> if when we returne, we doe bring ſtore of ſtrong wine (which they loue beyond meaſure) with it will vndertake ſo to charme this Dragon, that he ſhall do vs no harme.</p>
            <p>I, that for this end came from home, and in this iourney had taken much more paines to leſſe purpoſe, would verie gladlie from this mountaine haue taken ſo good a proofe to witnes my being in the countrey: but withall conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that not one <hi>Indian</hi> of our knowne friendes came vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs: that <hi>Don Iuan</hi> the coſen of <hi>Gualtero,</hi> who liueth here a
<pb facs="tcp:9768:18"/>
euolt from the Spaniard was now in election to bee chiefe commander of all the Indian forces in thoſe partes, cannot in pollicie, for <hi>Gualtero</hi> his ſake, whoſe inheritance he ſought to vſurpe, be a faſt friend vnto vs: that the Spaniards abiding in <hi>Winicapora</hi> (for there were ten) might well before wee could doe any thing, and returne, cauſe ſome others of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reo</hi> his men to ioyne with them, in the way to intercept vs: and forethinking withall, that there being no meanes, but by our ſelues to make known our diſcouerie, if we returned not; in our misfortune the hope of following this voyage would be buried: but beſides all this, and the reſpect of ſuch ſpyals, as the Spaniards kept to obſerue our dooings, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing that if the enemie ſhould by our lingring ſtop our paſſage, which in one or two places of aduantage, fewe of them might eaſilie doe: it would be a queſtion how with our ſhip to get out of the riuer, except firſt wee could remooue them: I thought it beſt (all other poſsibilities ſet apart) to ſeeke in time to bee free from the hazard of the forſaid euil paſſages.</p>
            <p>Whileſt we were ſearching at the ſhore for the <hi>Indians,</hi> my barge took a <hi>Canoa,</hi> with three men in her: the one a ſeruant to <hi>Berreo</hi> (as before is mentioned,) the other two marchants of <hi>Caſſaua.</hi> They had a letter ſent from the Gouernour to be coueied to <hi>Trinidado:</hi> which I receiued. There was alſo a great hatchet, and twentie kniues, wherewith this <hi>Indian</hi> ſeruant ſhould buy a <hi>Canoa,</hi> and hyre Indians to carie her vp the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer towards <hi>Nueuo Reyno.</hi> This <hi>Canoa</hi> forſooth with foure others was to be ſent to bring downe <hi>Berreo</hi> his ſonne with all his forces, which now haue bene I think, full three yeares in preparing, If fiue ſuch boates be ſufficient to conuoy him his men, and all their prouiſion: it may ſeeme, hee commeth with no great ſtrength.</p>
            <p>This ſeruant, as he was a man of eſpeciall truſt, and neer <hi>Berreo:</hi> ſo appeared hee to haue ſome inſight in his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. Hee ſhewed mee that the Indians, who with theſe
<pb facs="tcp:9768:18"/>
kniues ſhould be hired, were to paſſe vp ſo high, as where ſome of the <hi>Caſſanari</hi> do dwell in ſmall villages. That <hi>Berreo</hi> his purpoſe was, when they came thither to leaue them there, and make them his chiefe Officers ouer the other <hi>Indians:</hi> and in their places ſome of the <hi>Caſſanari</hi> ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, who likewiſe ſhould be made Iuſtices and Conſtables ouer them of <hi>Guiana:</hi> that from <hi>Trinidado</hi> he meant to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue moſt of the old inhabitants, that would be tractable; and interpoſe them amongſt the <hi>Caſſanarians</hi> of <hi>Guiana,</hi> and the <hi>Guianians</hi> of the <hi>Caſſanari.</hi> That the <hi>Arwaccas</hi> ſhould wholly poſſeſſe <hi>Trinidado,</hi> and the riuer ſide of <hi>Raleana.</hi> That they alreadie were prouided of threeſcore <hi>Negroes,</hi> to worke the mines in theſe places. And that by this meanes <hi>Berreo</hi> hoped to keepe theſe ſeuerall nations in mutual en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie each againſt other, all to ſerue his turne, and neuer to become ſtrong, or likelie to ioine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues againſt him. He farther ſhewed me that <hi>Topiawarie</hi> ſoone after our depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from the riuer, fled into the mountaines carrying <hi>Hugh Godwyn</hi> with him, and leauing a Subſtitute in his countrie, as aforeſaid: and that the next newes they heard of him was, that he was dead, and the Engliſh boy eaten by a Tyger. That the Spaniardes beleeue neither the one, nor the other. That about the end of Iune, when the riuer ſhall be impaſſable, the ten ſhips ſhall depart from <hi>Trinidado.</hi> And that <hi>Berreo</hi> euer ſince his comming to <hi>Guiana,</hi> hath ſpent his time altogether in purueying of victuals, whereof there is ſuch ſcarſitie, by reaſon that the Indians forſaking their houſes, haue not this half year planted any of their grounds, that the Spaniards are inforced to ſeeke their bread far off, and content themſelues to liue with little.</p>
            <p>In ſailing vp the riuer, we paſſed by <hi>Toparimacko</hi> his port, which in one place is verie ſhoald, the channell lying cloſe aboord the ſhoare. We returned therfore another way by the maine riuer on the South ſide: this branch we founde large, deep, and without danger. When we were come nere
<pb facs="tcp:9768:19"/>
               <hi>Carapana</hi> his port: he ſent fiue or ſixe ſeuerall <hi>Canoas,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing this day and the next, that he would come and ſpeak with vs. Thus we lingred ſix or ſeuen daies, but he came not. In the end hee ſent one of his aged followers, to certifie vs, that he was ſicke, olde and weake: that the wayes neere his dwelling are not eaſie: and that therefore he deſired vs to hold him excuſed for not comming. This olde man dilated vnto vs, that <hi>Carapana</hi> in hope of our returne, hath euer ſince your Lordſhips being in that countrie, kept the mountains, where the Spaniards can hardlie anie way inforce him; that they haue taken from him and his people, manie of their wiues, becauſe they refuſed to furniſh them weekelie with a certaine proportion of bread and victualles: that <hi>Don Iuan</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Eparacano</hi> hath the commandement of all his ſubiectes, excepting onelie a choiſe guarde of men ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to keep the place hee now dwelleth in. That it repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him of his ambition, euer to haue ſought by the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards meanes, to haue enlarged his countries and people. For true it is that from the beginning he was a Lord of no other then ordinarie power amongſt them, vntil he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into frinedſhip with <hi>Berreo:</hi> for then the Indians on all ſides left ſome their habitations, and manie their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders to become his ſubiectes, that ſo they might haue the priuiledge to trade with the Spaniards for hatchets and kniues, which are rare iewels of great price amongſt them. that he now ſaw no other choiſe, but that the <hi>Indians</hi> muſt, if they will doe well, without farther diſſembling of their neceſsitie, either entertaine vs their friends, or els giue place to the Spaniards their enemies. For the plentie of golde that is in this countrie, being now known and diſcouered, there is no poſsibilitie for them to keepe it: on the one ſide; they could feele no greater miſerie, nor feare more extremitie, then they were ſure to finde, if the Spaniardes preuayled, who perforce doe take all things from them, vſing them as their ſlaues, to runne, to rowe, to be their guides, to carrie
<pb facs="tcp:9768:19"/>
their burthens, and that which is worſt of all, to be content, for ſaftie of their liues, to leaue their women, if a Spaniard chaunce but to ſet his eie on anie of them to fancie her: on the other ſide; they could hope for, nor deſire no better ſtate and vſage, then her Maieſties gracious gouernment, and princelie vertues do promiſe, and aſſure vnto them. For, ſaid he, when the other yeare, we fled into the mountains, and meaſuring your doinges by the Spaniardes in like caſe, made no other account, but that your Commander being able, as he was, would doubtleſſe haue perſecuted vs to the vttermoſt, as the onlie maintaineres and ſupporters of your enemies, and would at the leaſt, if hee could not reach vs, take our townes, and make vs ranſome our wiues and children: we found it farre otherwiſe, and that none of your well gouerned companie durſt offer any of vs wrong or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, no not by ſtealth when vnknowne they might haue done it. We then beleeuing it to be true, that your grand Captaine reported of his Princeſſe, tooke this for a good proofe of her royall commandement and wiſedome, that had framed her ſubiects to ſuch obedience, and of your hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, that enioyed the benefite thereof: that <hi>Carapana</hi> weighing the good and friendlie courſe of our proceedings, doth humblie craue of her Maieſtie for himſelf and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that with the reſt of the <hi>Indians,</hi> which whollie depende on her princelie regard towards them; hee alſo may enioy her fauourable protection, that he doth this, not as a man left vnto himſelfe, and forſaken by the Spaniards, but as one that knoweth their iniuſtice hateth their cruelties, &amp; taketh it fos his beſt choiſe, vtterlie to diſclaime their friendſhip. It may bee pertinent (as ſurelie it is a thing worth the noting) to conſider how this preſident, of your moderation &amp; good order, which to vs ſeemeth a matter but of ſmal, and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie reſpect, hath both alienated their hearts altogether from the Spaniard, and ſtirred vp in them true loue and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration therof. For as gouernment is the only bond of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:9768:20"/>
ſocietie: ſo to men lawleſſe, that each one to another are, <hi>Omnes hoc iure moleſti, quo fortes:</hi> To men, I ſay, that liue in daylie tumultes, feares, doubtes, ſuſpitions, barbarous cruelties, neuer ſleeping ſecure, but alwaies either drunke, or practiſing one anothers death: to ſuch men as theſe be, who wanting diſcipline, iuſtice, &amp; good order to confirme them in a quiet and peaceable courſe of liuing knowe not where to find it: the ſence and ſweetneſſe thereof, is as the dewe of <hi>Hermon:</hi> it is as the harmonie of a well tuned Inſtrument: to be briefe, it carieth in it ſelfe not onlie a due and worthie commendation; but is auayleable without ſtroke ſtriking to gaine a kingdome. For the <hi>Indians</hi> in all partes within and neere the <hi>Guiana,</hi> doe offer their ſeruice, and promiſe to prouide victuall, and what els their countrie yeeldeth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring onlie that ſome force of men may remaine with them, to deliuer them from oppreſsion and tyrannie. And now by generall conſent (though hatchets and kniues be the onelie things of requeſt and vſefull vnto them) they haue agreed by no means to trade with the Spaniard for anie thing. Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this old man ſhewed me, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce moſt of their gold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that is formed in ſo manie &amp; diuers faſhions: whence their Spleene-ſtones, and others of all ſortes are to be had in plentie: where gold is to be gathered in the ſandes of their riuers: from what partes the Spaniards, both by trade, and otherwiſe, haue returned much golde. This he vttered with <hi>Carapana</hi> his conſent (I doubt not) hoping thereby to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce vs to returne againe. For contrarie to their lawe of ſecrecie, which in this caſe they doe all generallie obſerue, ſharplie puniſhing the breakers thereof, as enemies vnto their natiue countrie: I found this man no whit ſcrupulous, but verie free and liberall of ſpeech in all things.</p>
            <p>And becauſe we might know, that wee ſhould not want handes or helpe, in this or anie other our enterpriſes, if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps we ſhould find cauſe to paſſe vp to the head of this ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: he declared that the Spaniards haue no Indians to truſt
<pb facs="tcp:9768:20"/>
vnto but ſome of the <hi>Arwaccas,</hi> which ſince they were not manie could be but of ſmal force: That the <hi>Charibes</hi> of <hi>Gua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipa,</hi> the <hi>Crawannas</hi> amongſt the <hi>Tiuitiuas,</hi> the <hi>Shebaios, Iaos, Amaipagotos, Caſſipagotos, Putpagotos, Samipagotos, Serowos, Etaiguinams, Caſſamari,</hi> with the reſt of the nations farre and neere, were all readie, on what ſide ſoeuer the Spaniard ſhal ſtirre, to fight againſt them: that the <hi>Pariagotos,</hi> through whoſe country they muſt firſt paſſe, are alone ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter them, ſuch is the ſtrength of their countrie, and the valure of the men. The Indians hold opinion, that they are notable ſorcerers, and inuulnerable. In the mountains where they dwell white ſtones are founde of ſuch hardneſſe, that by no arte or meanes they can bee pearced: they imagine that theſe <hi>Pariagotos</hi> become inuulnerable, by eating theſe ſtones. The fable omitted, happelie they may prooue good Diamonds.</p>
            <p>Then hee ſhewed howe the <hi>Iwarewakeri</hi> haue nouriſhed graſſe in all places, where paſſage is, theſe three yeares, and that it is at this preſent ſo high as ſome of the trees; which they meane to burne, ſo ſoone as the Spaniard ſhall be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in danger thereof. Laſtlie, he ſhewed mee that <hi>Wariarima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goto</hi> the Emperours chiefe Captaine for thoſe partes, hath gathered together manie thouſands of the <hi>Epuremai,</hi> to keep the borders of the Empire; and that hee lay now on the ſouth ſide of the mountaines, ſome one dayes iourney, or little more from the Spaniard. To be ſhort, hee certified me, that they all were reſolued not to ſeeke vpon them (for indeed they feare their ſhot) but to defend their owne, and to expect our comming. In the meane time they take op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, when they finde anie of them ſtraggling or deuided from their ſtrength, by little &amp; little, to leſſen their number.</p>
            <p>The place, where we were at an ancor was but one daies iourney from <hi>Carapana:</hi> I therefore made motion to this Captaine to ſtaie with two or three of his company aboord
<pb facs="tcp:9768:21"/>
the ſhip, &amp; to cauſe his men to bring me with my Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Carapana</hi> his dwelling: he anſwered that it were not good ſo to doe, leaſt perhaps ſome Spie might informe the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> thereof, whereby daunger would growe to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rapana.</hi> For they haue manie times vſed manie meanes to reconcile him vnto them: but hee from time to time hath dalyed with them, neither profeſsing himſelfe their enemy, nor in aught ſhewing them anie friendſhip. Now ſaid hee) if the <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſhall by anie meanes come to knowledge, that you haue conferred together, they will take this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to perſecute him with all extremitie, as their open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, whom they now neglect, or at the leaſt feare not as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an harmeleſſe olde man. And for this cauſe onelie hath <hi>Carapana</hi> forborne to come vnto you.</p>
            <p>By this I perceiued, that to ſtay longer for him (though gladlie I could haue bene content to ſpende one ſeuenight more to ſpeake with him) would bee purpoſeleſſe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hauing aſſured ſo manie of the <hi>Indians,</hi> as at anie time came vnto vs, of our ſpeedie returne, promiſing them plenty of kniues, beades, and hatchets, if they would reſerue their <hi>Caſſaua,</hi> and prouide ſtore of their peeces of golde for vs: I deſired this Captaine to bee a meanes that our friendes of <hi>Trinidado</hi> might vnderſtand of our being in the riuer, and that wee meant to releeue them ſo ſoone, as conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlie might bee. Hee promiſed in <hi>Carapana</hi> his behalfe, that this ſhould not be forgotten. One of the Captaines of the <hi>Cyawannas,</hi> who doe now dwell in the riuer <hi>Arawawo,</hi> neere <hi>Trinidado,</hi> vndertooke alſo without faile to aſcertaine them thereof. I was the more carefull herein, becauſe ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhips being there, I doubted leaſt they would take order that no <hi>Indian</hi> ſhould ſpeake with vs. For ſo indeed it fell out.</p>
            <p>This Captain of the <hi>Cyawannas</hi> came likewiſe to ioyn with vs, and had prouided fifteen <hi>Canoas</hi> for that purpoſe. Their dwelling was lately in <hi>Macureo,</hi> wher the <hi>Spaniards</hi> one night
<pb facs="tcp:9768:21"/>
ſtealing on them, killed twentie of their men, and burnt their houſes, becauſe they refuſed to trade with them for certain images of gold made with manie heades, which they had gotten out of the <hi>Guiana.</hi> I ſent a preſent of Yron to <hi>Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pana,</hi> and then ſet ſaile.</p>
            <p>In turning downe the riuer we ſpent eight daies. In ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie places where the channell lyeth, wee found twentie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam depth: where it is ſholdeſt wee had two fadam and a halfe, and that but in one or two places. Of the woorthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this riuer, becauſe I cannot ſay ynough, I wil ſpeak nothing. Wee haue preſumed to call it by the name of <hi>Raleana,</hi> becauſe your ſelfe was the firſt of our nation that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer entred the ſame, and I thinke it nothing inferiour to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſones,</hi> which is beſt knowne by the name of <hi>Oreliana,</hi> the firſt diſcouerer thereof. By turning onlie, without helpe of owers, to paſſe ſo long a way, in ſo ſhorte a time, againſt the winde, may ſufficiently prooue, that the channell is verie large, good, and likelie to ſecond our hopes in all that we can deſire. Without the mouth of this riuer, our Pynnace, the <hi>Diſcouerer,</hi> whome wee loſt neere the coaſt of <hi>England,</hi> came vnto vs. She fel with this land ſomewhat to the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of <hi>Cape Cecyll,</hi> and had ſpent three weeks and od daies in ranging alongſt the coaſt, when ſhe met with vs. <hi>William Downe</hi> the Maiſter, informed me that they entred, &amp; ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched theſe foure riuers. In <hi>Wiapoco</hi> they ſayled ſo farre, vntil the rocks ſtopped their paſſage. In <hi>Caiane</hi> they went vp one dayes iourny. In <hi>Cunanama</hi> they found manie inhabitants. <hi>Curitini</hi> was the laſt riuer they had bene in. Whence, hauing no other means to find <hi>Raleana,</hi> they were inforced to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a Pilot againſt his wil: whom afterwards I would haue returned with reward to his contentment; but he would not.</p>
            <p>Our Engliſh that to ſteale the firſt bleſsing of an vntra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded place, will perhaps ſecretlie haſten thither, may bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to me for this caueat, if they take notice thereof. They may be aſſured, that this people, as they no way ſought
<pb facs="tcp:9768:22"/>
our harme, but vſed our men with all kindneſſe: ſo are they impacient of ſuch a wrong, as to haue anie of their people perforce taken from them, and will doubtleſſe ſeek reuenge. The example of the like practiſe vpon the coaſt of <hi>Ginnie,</hi> in the yeare 1566. and againe at <hi>Dominica,</hi> where Alderman <hi>Wats</hi> his ſhip hardlie eſcaped being taken may ſerue for our warning in like caſe to looke for no good, before they bee ſatisfied for this iniurie.</p>
            <p>When we had taken aboord vs ſuch victuals as were in the Pynnace: we ſet fire in her, (for her Rudder could ſerue her to no longer vſe) and ſtopping the flouds, plyed to wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with the ebbe neere the ſhoare, vntill we were ſixteen leagues to the Eaſtward of the riuers mouth, and then ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding off to ſea, we fell in 24. houres ſayling with <hi>Punto Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lera</hi> the Northeaſtermoſt part of <hi>Trinidado.</hi> But hauing <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco</hi> Iland in ſight, we firſt went thither. This Iland is plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull of all thinges, and a very good ſoyle. It is not nowe inhabited, becauſe the <hi>Charibes</hi> of <hi>Dominica,</hi> are euil neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours vnto it. They of <hi>Trinidado</hi> haue a meaning and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to flie thither, when no longer they can keep <hi>Trinida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do.</hi> Their onlie doubt is, that when they are ſeated there, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> will ſeeke to poſſeſſe it alſo. The Gouernour of <hi>Marguerita</hi> went latelie in a pynnace to viewe this Iland. <hi>Gilbert</hi> my Pylot who ſomtime liued there, noteth it for the beſt and fruitfulleſt ground that he knoweth.</p>
            <p>Thence we returned to <hi>Punto Gallera</hi> and ancored in ten fadam vnder the northſide of the Ilande ſome fiue or ſixe miles from the ſaid point. The floud-tyde ſtriketh alongſt the coaſt to the Eaſtward verie ſtronglie. Wee diſcharged a peece of ordinance, and afterwardes went to the ſhoare in our boat: but no <hi>Indian</hi> came vnto vs. I would haue ſent <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Trinidado</hi> to procure ſome of them to ſpeake with vs: but he was altogether vnwilling, alleadging that their dwellings were farre within the mountaines, and that he knew no part of that ſide of the Iland. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this place we ſet ſaile for S. <hi>Luce</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9768:22"/>
but fell with the <hi>Granadas,</hi> which we found not inhabited, S. <hi>Vincent</hi> we hardly recouered by turning vnder the liegh of the Iland. The <hi>Tobacco</hi> of this place is good: but the <hi>Indians</hi> being <hi>Canibals,</hi> promiſing vs ſtore, and delaying vs from day to day, ſought onlie opportunitie to betray, take and eat vs, as latelie they had deuoured the whole companie of a French ſhip This their treacherie being by one of their ſlaues reuealed, from thencefoorth they did all forbeare to come vnto vs. To ſit downe on their lowe ſtooles, when they by offring ſuch eaſe, will ſeeme to ſhewe curteſie, abodeth death to ſtrangers, that ſhall truſt them. At <hi>Matalino</hi> wee found not any inhabitants. Laſtlie, wee came to <hi>Dominica,</hi> where we could get no good Tobacco. But hauing intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of a Spaniſh ſhip, that was taking in of freſh water, at the northweſt ſide of the Iland; we wayed ancor to ſeek him He deſcrying vs, ſtole away by night. The <hi>Indians</hi> of this place haue determined to remooue, and ioyne with them of <hi>Guanipa,</hi> againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who lately diſpeopled one of their Ila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, &amp; at our being ther, one of their <hi>Canoas</hi> returned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Guanipa,</hi> &amp; certified vs, that the ten Spaniſh ſhips at <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nidado,</hi> do ride ſome of them at <hi>Conquerabia,</hi> the reſt at the ſmall Ilandes neere the difimboging place. Herehence wee ſteered North and by Eaſt, taking the directeſt courſe to ſhorten our way homewards.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I emptied your purſe, ſpending my time and trauell in following your Lordſhips directions for the full diſcouery of this coaſt, and the riuers thereof. Concerning the not making of a voyage for your priuate profit, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend nothing. Sorie I am, that where I ſought no excuſe, by the Spaniards being there, I founde my defect remedileſſe. And for mine owne part, I doe proteſt, that if the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the publike good, that may enſue, had not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyſed all other hopes, and deſires: I would rather haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured by ſuch ſmall and weake meanes as I had, to doe well with danger, then to returne onlie with ſafetie. Now
<pb facs="tcp:9768:23"/>
although in a cauſe not doubtfull, my allegation is no way needfull: yet becauſe the waightineſſe thereof, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of others, ſeemeth of due &amp; right to claime, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be ſaid by me whom your eſpecial truſt and fauour hath credited and graced with this imployment: Pardon it (I beſeech your Honour) if, where my lamp had oile, it bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row light alſo; and my ſpeech, which is altogether vnſauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſeaſon it ſelfe with ſome of the leauen of your own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe touching this diſcouerie. The particular relation of ſome certaine thinges, I haue reſerued, as properlie belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to your ſelfe, who onlie, as knowing moſt, can make beſt vſe thereof. So much in generall is here touched, as (I hope) may ſerue to refreſh the memorie of this worthie enterpriſe in thoſe whom it may concerne, and teſtifie your care and expence in following the ſame: That in a ſecond age, when in time truth ſhall haue credite, and men woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering at the richeſſe, and ſtrength of this place, which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture her ſelfe hath marueilouſlie fortified, as her chiefe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure houſe, ſhal mourn and ſigh to hold idle cickles, whileſt others reap, &amp; gather in this harueſt: it be not ſaid, that Sir <hi>Walter Ralegh</hi> was of al men liuing in his daies, moſt indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious in ſeeking moſt fortunat in attaining to the fulnes of an ineſtimable publique good: if, knowing that for enuy &amp; priuate reſpectes, his labors were leſſened, his informations miſtruſted, his proffers not regarded and the due honour of his deſerts imparted to others If (I ſay) ſeeing, knowing and bearing all this, hee with patience had perſiſted in ſo good a way of doing his Princeſſe, and countrie ſeruice; and had but perfected his firſt diſcouerie by ſending a ſhip, or two for that purpoſe: for then ſurelie all lets &amp; doubts being remooued, and ſo large a kingdome, ſo exceeding rich, ſo plentifull of all things, as this by his diſcourſe, appeared to be, being offered: no deuiſes, and vaine ſurmiſes could haue taken place, no illuſions could haue preuayled, it had been blindneſſe and deafneſſe in thoſe that being neere her
<pb facs="tcp:9768:23"/>
Maieſtie: do ſpend their daies in ſeruing the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale, not to ſee, and know in ſo waightie a matter: it had beene malicious obſtinacie, impotencie of minde, and more then treaſon to the common wealth, the matter ſtanding onlie vpon acceptance, to ſeeke either to foreſlowe ſo fit an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or forſake ſo generall a bleſsing. This, if, is nowe cut off through a ſingular and incomparable temper, in ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming euill with good: This your ſecond diſcouerie hath not onlie found a free &amp; open entrance into <hi>Raleana,</hi> which the Naturals call <hi>Orenoque:</hi> but moreouer yeeldeth choiſe of fourtie ſeuerall great riuers (the leſſer I doe not recken) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the moſt part with ſmall veſſels nauigable, for our merchants and others, that doe now finde little profit in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth for repriſall, to exerciſe trade in. To ſuch as ſhall be willing to aduenture in ſearch of them, I could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſome hope of gold mines, &amp; certain aſſurance of peeces of made golde, of Spleen-ſtones, Kidney-ſtones, and others of better eſtimate: but becauſe our beleefe ſeemeth to bee mated in theſe greater matters, &amp; a certaintie of ſmaller pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, is the readieſt inducement to quicken our weak hopes; I not going ſo far as mine own eyes might warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me, do onlie promiſe in theafore ſaid riuers, Braſil wood, honey, Cotten, <hi>Balſamu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp; drugs to help defray charges: &amp; farther, becauſe without a beginning there can bee no continuance of theſe benefits vnto our country, to anie that ſhalbe the firſt vnder takers hereof, I am gladly content, to giue ſuch light &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge, as by confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with the <hi>Indians</hi> I haue attained vnto.</p>
            <p>My ſelfe, and the remaine of my few yeares, I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed whollie to <hi>Raleana,</hi> and all my thoughtes liue only in that action. The proſecuting whereof is in it ſelf iuſt, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and neceſſarie. Iuſt: becauſe it is intended for the defence of harmeleſſe people, who fearing thraldom, and oppreſsion, deſire to protect themſelues and their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey vnder her Maieſties tuition: Profitable, as may bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered not onlie by manie Spaniſh letters intercepted, but
<pb facs="tcp:9768:24"/>
alſo by the proofes mentioned in the diſcourſe of the firſt diſcouery, and ſince that, by the <hi>Indians</hi> owne voluntarie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations: and laſtlie, by the prouiſion that the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> doe make to acquite vs thereof. Neceſſarie it is, as being the onlie help to put a byt in the mouth of the vnbrideled <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard;</hi> the onlie way to enter into his treaſurie of <hi>Nueuo Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> and <hi>Peru;</hi> the onlie means to animate the wronged <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> with our aſsiſtance, to ſeeke reuenge for the extreame murthers and cruelties, which they haue endured, and to ruinate his naked cities in all thoſe partes of the Inlande, whoſe foundations haue beene laid in the bloud of their parents and anceſtors.</p>
            <p>The forces that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> hath alreadie ſent to <hi>Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dado,</hi> to fortifie there, and keep the paſſage of this riuer, are an euident argument, that the king feareth and doubteth the ſequele of this diſcouerie. For can it bee a ſmall matter? or hath he ſo waſte imployment for his men and ſhipping, that vpon no ground, he would ſend 28. ſhippes, to keepe vs onlie from <hi>Tobacco?</hi> (for what els that good is can <hi>Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dado</hi> yeeld vs?) no, doubtleſſe, if the returne of <hi>Berreo</hi> his Campe-maiſter with ten of theſe ſhippes, bee compared with precedent aduertiſments concerning him: it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare more then probable, that the <hi>Guiana</hi> golde waged theſe men and ſhipping: and that they are now more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to obtaine this place, then to keepe others, which they haue alreadie gotten, which note except in matters of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie account, is not incident to their pollicie and proceedings. Againe, it cannot be thought but that either it was ſenceleſſe madneſſe in the gouernours of <hi>Marguerita,</hi> and the <hi>Caraccas</hi> to bring their ſtates, and liues in queſtion, by ſeeking contrarie to their kings order, to enter the <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana,</hi> and kill <hi>Berreo</hi> with his his followers: or els the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of pearle in <hi>Marguerita,</hi> and the golde mines in the <hi>Caraccas,</hi> ſeeming matters of ſmall account: the <hi>Guiana</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie was in their iudgement, rich, plentifull, and able of it
<pb facs="tcp:9768:24"/>
ſelfe to redeeme their treſpaſſe and offence, how great ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it ſhould be.</p>
            <p>The ſundry attempts and ouerthrowes of the Spaniards being men of power, and honourable place, in labouring theſe 63. yeares, and vpwards to inlarge the kingdome of <hi>Spaine,</hi> with this mightie and great Empire, doe plainlie ſhow, that they long time ſought a path, where in one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a high way was found: that the loſſe of their liues wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth their deſires, &amp; the worthineſſe of the thing, where to vs the eaſineſſe of obtaining diſcrediteth the greatneſſe of the attempt: and that if now at the laſt they doe preuaile, they muſt holde by tyrannie that which they get by the ſword; where then our returne nothing by the <hi>Indians</hi> is more wiſhed for, nothing expected more earneſtly.</p>
            <p>Thoſe obiections, which haue bene made by manie ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming wiſe, and the impediments likelie to ariſe, as they haue ſuppoſed, are beſt anſwered by the vnreprooued witneſſe of theſe mens actions. Some haue tearmed theſe diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries fables, and fantaſies, as if there had bene no ſuch land, or territorie: others allowing both of the place, and that ſuch a kingdome or country is diſcouered, make concluſion that if it had beene ſo rich, as wee haue ſuppoſed: that no doubt the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> would by this time haue poſſeſt it. But if they conſider that the Spaniſh-nation hath already conquered the two Empires of <hi>Mexico,</hi> and <hi>Peru,</hi> with ſo manie other kingdomes and prouinces: wee may very well anſwere, that his power is not infinite, and that hee hath done well for the time. And yet it is manifeſt, that this very Empire hath beene by all thoſe ſeuerall Spaniards (the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of whoſe names, is by it ſelfe hereunto annexed) at ſundrie times vndertaken, and neuer performed. Howbeit, the world hath reaſon to admire their conſtancie, and their great labours, and we may well bluſh at our owne idle, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairefull, and loytering diſpoſitions, that can find abilitie in another barren, and ſterued nation, to poſſeſſe ſo much of
<pb facs="tcp:9768:25"/>
the worlde: and can doe nothing but frame argumentes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſelues as vnfit and powerleſſe to poſſeſſe one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince already diſcouered and of which our nation hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of the peoples loue, and that all the Chieftaines and principalles haue vowed their obedience and ſeruice to her Maieſtie; the nauigation being withall ſo ſhort, dangerleſſe and free from infectious ſickneſſe. If doubt of perils might moderate the mindes of men once mooued with ſtedfaſt hope, that golde ſhall be the reward of their trauels: it may eaſilie be perceiued that all thoſe lettes and hinderances, that can anie way bee alleadged, or wreſted ſo much, as but to touch vs, doe deeply and neerelie concerne the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh king, and in a manner violentlie with-holde him from that, which he notwithſtanding carieth with ſucceſſe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt we out of ſeaſon, doe affect the bare ſtyle, to bee named men ſtayed and circumſpect in our proceedings. It is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that <hi>Calanus</hi> the <hi>Indian</hi> threw downe before <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, a drie ſeare peece of leather, and then put his foot on one of the endes of it: the leather being trode downe on that ſide, roſe on all partes els. By this the wiſe man did ſhewe vnto him a figure and ſimilitude of his kingdome, which being exceeding large, muſt of neceſsitie in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther partes excepting the place of the kings reſidence, bee alwayes ful of ſtirres, tumults, &amp; inſurrections. The end after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards confirmed, that this Empire conſiſting of ſundry na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, could not keep it ſelfe from diſſolution. No potentate liuing hath, or can haue ſo faithful &amp; incorrupt Counſellers, as be the examples and hiſtories of fore paſſed ages. Wee may therefore be bold to thinke that the Gouernours of the Spaniſh affaires ſhould mind it, that their kings luſtfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and ambicious thoughtes to eſtabliſh ouer all <hi>Europe</hi> one lawe, one Lord, one religion, are built and erected on a dangerous vngrounded reſolution: Conſidering that many of the neighbour kingdomes being of equall force in men, or greater then he can make, are ſetled in a long continued
<pb facs="tcp:9768:25"/>
eſtate, are entire within themſelues, and hate to heare the voyce of a ſtranger. It is not vnlikelie that they in this caſe ſhoulde lay before their king the fatall deſtinies of manie Worthies, that haue beene conſtrayned for want of ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient numbers of their naturall ſubiectes, after manie yeares ſpent in the warres, to retyre to their owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and haue bene glad peaceablie to hold their owne Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niories at home, reſigning all that vnto others, which they haue gotten abroad by hard aduenture, and much effuſion of blood. The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> cannot but diſcerne, that his ſpacious Empires and kingdomes being ſo manie, and ſo farre diuided one from another, are like the members of a monſtrous bodie, tyed together with cables onlie For take away the trafique of vnneceſſarie commodities tranſported out of <hi>Spaine:</hi> thoſe huge countries of the <hi>Indies</hi> hauing no common linke of affinity, lawe, language, or religion, and being of themſelues able to maintaine themſelues without forreine commerce, are not ſo ſimple, as not to know their owne ſtrength, and to finde, that they doe rather poſſeſſe <hi>Spaniardes,</hi> then that they are poſſeſſed by them. He cannot be ignorant that <hi>Spaine</hi> it ſelf is on all ſides enuironed with many puiſant enemies, mighty &amp; great princes, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be rich without men, confident without reaſon, proud &amp; aduenturous without means ſufficient; may happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie confederate to chaſtiſe him, as an inſolent intruder, and diſturber of all quietneſſe; and going no farther then <hi>Spaine</hi> it ſelfe, may euen there ſhake the foundation of his long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triued deuiſes, and in one act redeeme the time, controll his aſpiring humor, and breake the bandes in ſunder, that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port ſeruitude, and ſubuerſion to all the dominions of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome. Againe, his counſell may well informe him, that to diſpeople and diſable himſelfe at home, in hope to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the <hi>Guiana,</hi> being a countrey ſtrong of it ſelfe, and defended with infinite multitudes of <hi>Indian</hi> enemies, being rich, and by the inhabitantes offered vnto the Engliſh: his
<pb facs="tcp:9768:26"/>
contempt towards vs would ſeeme ſo intollerable and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpightfull as might be ſufficient to prouoke vs, though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we had no ſuch inclination; if he vnprouided of able helpes to effect it, ſhould reſt himſelfe on a careleſſe preſumption, that we cannot, we dare not we will not ſtirre in a matter that promiſeth vs ſo great benefite, and may ſo highlie offend him. He may be perſwaded, that to leaue no other ſuccour or ſaftie to his nakednes, but the olde, ſtale practiſe of ſpreading rumours, and giuing out falſe intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of preparations to inuade <hi>England,</hi> thereby to keepe vs at home; or els of hyring and ſuborning ſome <hi>Machaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> vnder hand by ſecrete conueyance, to ſtop the courſe of our proceedings; or laſtlie, of procuring ſome wilde out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law to diſquiet our tranquilitie; is but a poore, weake, and vncertaine ſtaie to vphold his eſtate by. And yet ſetting ſuch like driftes aſide: what can be imagined likelie to hinder vs from preuailing in the <hi>Guiana,</hi> rather then him, whoſe diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage it is to be encombred with the ſelf ſame, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold more impedimentes, then can any way bee ſuppoſed, with good cauſe to impeach, or diuorce vs from ſo profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an attempt? All this notwithſtanding, if the Spaniſh king not being able to diſſemble his deſire, or beare the loſſe of this one kingdome; putting himſelfe out of his ſtrength at home, and expoſing his people to the hazarde of all caſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties abroad, be reſolued whatſoeuer ſhall happen, not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh the <hi>Guiana,</hi> but to keep this one Iron more in the fire, on no other aſſurance, but a peremptorie diſdaine of preuention: If he appeare ſo eagerlie bent for the <hi>Guiana,</hi> as if it were enacted for a lawe amongſt themſelues, <hi>Viis &amp; modis</hi> to thruſt for it and not to heare, conceiue, or beleeue anie thing, that may diſſwade or deter them from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt thereof: It then appertayneth vnto vs, not to inforce thoſe obiections againſt our ſelues, which he with leſſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon reiecteth, as friuolous; ſince by how much the more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt hee is in following this purpoſe: by ſo much the leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:9768:26"/>
cauſe haue we to be diuerted from it. To ſuch as ſhall bee willing farther to wade in this argument; fos breuities ſake, I doe propoſe onlie this bare aſſertion: that <hi>England</hi> &amp; the <hi>Guiana</hi> conioyned, are ſtronger, and more eaſilie defended, then if <hi>England</hi> alone, ſhould repoſe her ſelfe on her owne force, and poerfulneſſe. The reaſons that might be inferred to prooue this, need no rationall diſcourſe: they are all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated in the onlie example of <hi>Spaine</hi> it ſelfe; which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Indies,</hi> is but a purſe without money, or a painted ſheath without a dagger. In ſum: it ſeemeth vnto me that whereas the difficultie of performing this enterpriſe, hath bene produced for a diſcouragment: it were a dull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of ſtrange weaknes in our ſelues, to diſtruſt our own power ſo much; or at leaſt, our owne hearts and courages; as valewing the Spaniſh nation to be omnipotent; or yeelding that the poore <hi>Portugall</hi> hath that maiſtering ſpirite, and conquering induſtrie, aboue vs; as to be able to ſeat him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe amongſt the manie mighty princes of the Eaſt <hi>Indies,</hi> to frontier <hi>China,</hi> to holde in ſubiection the <hi>Philippines, Zei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan, Calecut, Goa, Ormus, Mozambique,</hi> and the reſt; the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigation being ſo tedious and full of perill: to ſuffer our ſelues to be put backe for worthleſſe cyphers, out of place, without account. All which Regions being now alſo by the late conqueſt of <hi>Portugall,</hi> entituled to the Spaniſh king: to whome the <hi>Colenies</hi> of thoſe partes doe yet generallie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to ſweare fealtie and allegeance: and the care depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on him, not onlie of gouerning them in the Eaſt, ſo farre off; but alſo of ordering and ſtrengthening of thoſe diſvnited, ſcattered, and ill guarded Empires and prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Weſt: It might verie well be alleadged to the ſaid Spaniſh king, that it were more wiſedome for him to aſſure and fortifie ſome part of thoſe already gotten then to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the conqueſt of <hi>Guiana,</hi> ſo farre ſeperate from the reſt of his <hi>Indies:</hi> in which he hath had ſo manie misfortunes, and againſt whome the naturall people are ſo impetuouſlie
<pb facs="tcp:9768:27"/>
bent and oppoſed: were it not, that it exceedeth all the reſt in aboundance of gold, and other riches. The caſe then ſo ſtanding: is it not meere wretchedneſſe in vs, to ſpend our time breake our ſleep, and waſte our braines, in contriuing a cauelling falſe title to defraude a neighbour of halfe an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kor of land: whereas here whole ſhyeres of fruitfull rich groundes lying now waſte for want of people, doe proſtitute themſelues vnto vs like a faire and beautifull woman, in the pride and flower of deſired yeares?</p>
            <p>If we doe but conſider, howe vnhappelie <hi>Berreo</hi> his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, with his aſsiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts haue of late years, in our own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſucceeded: who can ſay, if the hand of the Almighty be not againſt them, and that he hath a work in this place, in ſteed of Papiſtrie to make the ſyncere light of his Goſpell to ſhine on this people? The effecting whereof ſhall bee a royall crowne of euerlaſting remembrance to all other bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, that from the beginning, the Lord hath plentifullie poured on our dread Soueraigne, in an eminent, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame degree of all perfection. If the <hi>Caſtilians</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a religious care of planting Chriſtianitie in thoſe partes, haue in their doings preached nought els but aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, rapine, blood, death, and deſtruction to thoſe naked, ſheeplike creatures of God; erecting Statues and Trophees of victorie vnto themſelues, in the ſlaughters of millions of Innocents: doth not the crie of the poore ſuccourleſſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend vnto the heauens? Hath God forgotten to be gracious vnto the workmanſhip of his owne hands? or ſhall not his iudgementes in a day of viſitation by the miniſterie of his<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> choſen ſeruant, come on theſe bloodthirſtie butchers, like raine into a fleece of wooll? <hi>Aliquando manifeſta, aliquando <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>cculta: ſemper iuſta ſunt Dei iudicia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To leaue this digreſsion. It is fit onelie for a Prince to beginne, and ende this worke: the maintenance and ordering thereof requireth Soueraigne power, authoritie and commandement. The riuer of <hi>Raleana</hi> giueth open and
<pb facs="tcp:9768:27"/>
free paſſage, anie prouiſion that the Spaniard can make to the contrarie, notwithſtanding; (for once yearelie the lands neere the riuer be all drowned) to conuey men, horſe, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, and victuall for anie power of men, that ſhall be ſent thither.</p>
            <p>I doe ſpeake it on my ſoules health as the beſt teſtimony, that I can in any cauſe yeeld, to auerre a trueth, that hauing now the ſecond time bene in this countrie, &amp; with the helps of time, and leiſure well aduiſed my ſelfe vpon all circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to be thought on; I can diſcerne no ſufficient impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment to the contrarie, but that with a competent number of men, her Maieſtie may to her and her ſucceſſors, enioy this rich and great empire: and hauing once planted there, may for euer (by the fauour of God) hold and keepe it, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Iudaeos &amp; Gentes.</hi> Subiects, I doubt not, may through her Maieſties gracious ſufferance, ioyning their ſtrength toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, inuade, ſpoile, and ouerrunne it, returning with golde and great riches. But what good of perpetuitie can followe thereof? Or who can hope that they will take any other courſe, then ſuch, as tendeth to a priuate and preſent bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite; conſidering that an Empire once obtained, is of congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie, how, and whereſoeuer the charge ſhall grow, to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed vnto the Crowne? The riches of this place are not fit for anie priuate eſtate: no queſtion, they wil rather proue ſufficient to croſſe, and counteruaile the Spaniard his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in all partes of Chriſtendome, where his money maketh way to his ambition.</p>
            <p>If the neceſsitie of following this enterpriſe do nothing vrge vs, becauſe in ſome caſe better a miſchiefe, then an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience: let the conueniencie thereof ſomewat mooue vs, in reſpect both of ſo manie Gentlemen, ſouldiours, and younger brothers, who, if they for want of imployment, doe not die like cloyed cattell in ranck eaſefulneſſe; are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced for maintenance ſake, ſometimes to take ſhamefull and vnlawfull courſes: and in reſpect of ſo manie handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craftſmen
<pb facs="tcp:9768:28"/>
hauing able bodies, that doe liue in cleanneſſe of teeth, and pouertie. To ſacrifice the children of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale vnto <hi>Beliall,</hi> is not to defile the land with blood, becauſe the law of God doth not prohibit it, and the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of iuſtice requireth it to bee ſo: but yet if the water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boughes, that ſucke and feed on the iuice, and nouriſhment that the fruitfull branches ſhould liue by, are to be cut down from the tree, and not regarded: luckie, and proſperous be that right hand, that ſhal plant and poſſeſſe with a ſoyle, where they may fructifie, increaſe, and growe to good: thriſe honourable and bleſſed be the memorie of ſo charitable a deed, from one generation to another.</p>
            <p>To conclude. Your Lordſh. hath paid for the Diſcouery and ſearch, both in your owne perſon, and ſince by me. You haue framed it, and moulded it readie for her Maieſtie: to ſet on her ſeale. If either enuie or ignorance, or other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe fruſtrate the reſt, the good which ſhall growe to our enemies, and the loſſe which will come to her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and this kingdome, will after a fewe yeares ſhewe it ſelfe. Wee haue more people, more ſhippes, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meanes, and yet doe nothing. The Spaniſh king hath had ſo ſweete a taſte of the riches thereof, as notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that hee is Lord of ſo manie Empires and kingdomes alreadie, notwithſtanding his enterpriſes of <hi>Fraunce</hi> and <hi>Flaunders,</hi> notwithſtanding that hee attended this yeare a home inuaſion: yet he ſent twentie eight ſaile to <hi>Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dado,</hi> whereof ten were for that place, and <hi>Guiana,</hi> and had ſome other ſhippes readie at <hi>Cades,</hi> if the ſame had not beene by my Lord, her Maieſties Generall and your Lordſhip ſet on fyre.</p>
            <p>In one word. The time ſerueth, the like occaſion ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome happeneth in manie ages, the former repeated con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations doe all iointlie together importune vs, nowe, or neuer to make our ſelues rich, our poſteritie happie, our Prince euerie way ſtronger the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our enemies, and to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh
<pb facs="tcp:9768:28"/>
our Countrey in a ſtate flouriſhing and peaceable. O lett not then ſuch an indignitie reſt on vs, as to depraue ſo notable an enterpriſe with falſe rumors, and vaine ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, to ſleepe in ſo ſerious a matter, and renouncing the honour, ſtrength, wealth, and ſoueraingtie of ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous conqueſt, to leaue all vnto the Spaniard.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>A Table of the names of the Riuers, Townes, and <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiques or Captaines that in this ſecond</hi> Voyage diſcouered.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                     <cell role="label">Riuers.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Nations.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Townes</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Captain.</cell>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Arrowari</hi> great.</cell>
                     <cell>Arwaos Pararweas. <hi>Charibes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>1 Theſe are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Iaos, their money is of white and greene ſtones. They ſpeak the Tiuitiuas lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: ſo likewiſe doe the nation of the Arricarri, who haue greater ſtore of thoſe moneyes then any others.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Iwaripoco.</hi> very great.</cell>
                     <cell>Mapurwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aos.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>2 Here it was, as it ſemeth, that Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Piuzon, the Spaniard, had his Emeralds. In one of theſe two riuers, certain French me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſuffered ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack ſome two or three yeares ſince, do liue.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Maipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Arricarri.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell rows="3">3. 4. 5. Theſe with the other 2 ſeem to be branches of the great riuer of Ama<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zones. When wee firſt fell with land, wee were, by the Indians re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, but one dayes ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from the greateſt riuer, that is on that coaſt.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Caipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogh. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Arricurri.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Arcooa. g</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Marowan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas. <hi>Cha.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Wiapoco. g</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Coonoracki Wacacoia. Wariſeaco. <hi>Charib.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>6 The firſt mountains that appear within land doe lie on the Eaſt ſide of this riuer. From the mouth thereof, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants do paſſe with their Canoas in twenty daies to the ſalt lake, where <hi>Manoa</hi> ſtandeth. The water hath manie Cateractes like <hi>Caroli,</hi> but that they are of greater diſtance one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another. where it falles into the ſea, hilles doe incloſe it, on both ſides.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Wanari.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9768:29"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Capur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wacka. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Charibes.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cawo. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Iaos.</cell>
                     <cell>Ico oma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</cell>
                     <cell>Wareo.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Wia. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Maworia. <hi>Charib.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Paramo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na. g.</cell>
                     <cell>Maſhwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po</cell>
                     <cell>10 The Freſhet ſhoots out into the ſea, with great force: the ſea doth here ſometimes campe high, and breake, as if it were full of rockes. but in prooffe it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but the pride and force of the tydes. In this baye, and round about, ſo farre as the mountaines doe extend there is great ſtore of Braſill wood, ſome of it bearing far darker col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour then other ſome. Here are alſo manie ſortes of other good woods.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Caiane. g.</hi> Gowateri: a great Iland</cell>
                     <cell>Wiaco. Ch. Shebaios.</cell>
                     <cell>Canawi, g Orinike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro.</cell>
                     <cell>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>watteo.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Macuria.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Piraos. Ch.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cawro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ra</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Arawaccos <hi>Charib.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Manma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuri.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Ipaios. Ch.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>14 Theſe ſpeake the language of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians of <hi>Dominicae.</hi> They are but few, but verie cruell to their enemies. For they bind, and eat them aliue peece-meale. This tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to the ded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie pains that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of hurtes, or woundes, made by thoſe arrowes that ar inuenomed with the iuice of the hearbe <hi>Wapototo.</hi> Theſe Indians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they eat the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom they kill, vſe no poyſon. The ſea coaſt is no where populous, for they haue much waſted themſelues in mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall warres. But now in all partes ſo farre as <hi>Orenoque,</hi> they liue in league and peace.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cureey.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Shebaios.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Curaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wini.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Shebaios.</cell>
                     <cell>Muſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra. g.</cell>
                     <cell>Ocapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9768:29"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cunana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Iaos. Arwaccas.</cell>
                     <cell>Waritappi. g</cell>
                     <cell>Carinama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri. Curipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toore.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>racco.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Arwaccas.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Marwabo.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Moruga.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Arwaccas.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Eramacoa.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mawari.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Winicinas Arwaccas.</cell>
                     <cell>Iwanama.</cell>
                     <cell>Atanacoa.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mawar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pari.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Arwaccas.</cell>
                     <cell>Awaricana.</cell>
                     <cell>Mahaho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nero.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Amonna.</hi> very great <hi>Capeleppo. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Charibes.</cell>
                     <cell>Iaremappo <hi>very great.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>21 Nere the head of this riuer, <hi>Cape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leppo</hi> falleth out of the plaines, &amp; run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth into the ſea with <hi>Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>itini.</hi> Some of the Guianians liue in this riuer.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Marawi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Paracuttos</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Owcowi.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Wiawiami</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Arama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tappo.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Wiapo.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Macuru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Carapi.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>29</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Vraca.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <p n="29">29. This riuer, as also moſt of the reſt, is not nauigable aboue ſix daies iourney by reaſon of rockes. It is ten daies iorney to the heade, where the Guianians do dwel Honey, yarne of Cotton, Silke, Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamum, and Braſill beddes are hereto bee had in plentie, and ſo all the coaſt alongſt Eaſtwarde. Some Images of Golde, ſpleene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones, and others, may bee gotten on this coaſt, but they doe ſomewhat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinariliy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme of them, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe euery where they are current money. They get their Moones, and other peeces of gold by exchange, taking for ech one of their greater Canoas, one peece or image of golde, with three heads, and after that rate for their leſſer Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noas, they receiue peeces of golde of leſſe value. One hatchet is the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary price for a Canoa They haue euery where diuers ſortes of drugges, Gummes, &amp; rootes which I doubt, not by father tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>al, will be found medicinable</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Names of poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hearbes.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Ourari. Caraſſi. Apa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eepo. Parapara.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Hea be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt poyſon.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Turara. Cutarapama. Wapo. Macatto.</p>
                        <p>The 29. day of Iune we arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in Portland Roade, hauing ſpente fiue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths in going, ſtaying, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning.</p>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9768:30"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Chaima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winini. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Carepini. <hi>Charib.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>31</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ecrowio.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Pawro.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Vpotom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas. Arwaccas.</cell>
                     <cell>Maripom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</cell>
                     <cell>Caponaia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>33</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Shurina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Carepini. <hi>Cha.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>34</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Shurama. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Carepini. <hi>Cha.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Cupari.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Northu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>briae, or Cupana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma. very g</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Arwaccas.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Wioma.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cuſhwini.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Neekcari.</cell>
                     <cell>Tawrooro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mene</cell>
                     <cell>Neperwari.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Inana. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Curitini. g</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Carepini. Arwaccas. Parawianni</cell>
                     <cell>Owaripoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Mawrona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. Maiapoore Cariwacka. Aneta. Manaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beece.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Winitwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Eppera. Parawian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Berbice. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Arwaccas.</cell>
                     <cell>Lupulee.</cell>
                     <cell>Warawa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roco.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Wapari.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Shebaios. Arwaccas.</cell>
                     <cell>Madewini.</cell>
                     <cell>Benmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wagh.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Maica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wini.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Panapi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ccas.</cell>
                     <cell>Itewee.</cell>
                     <cell>Caporaco. <hi>great Cap.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Maha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waica.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Arwaccas.</cell>
                     <cell>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ureſa g</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9768:30"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> e. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>wacawaios. Arwaccas.</cell>
                     <cell>Mabureſa. g</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell rows="8"> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>46</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">So called af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the name of the right ho. the Earle of Eſſex.</note>
                        <hi>Deuoritia, or Deſſekebe. very g. Matorooni. Coowini. Chipanama. Arawanna. Itorebece.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Iaos. Shebaios. Arwaccas. Char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bes. Maripai. wocowaios Parawianni Iwarwacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>47</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Pawrooma. g. Aripacoro. Ecawini. Manuriwini.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Iaos. Panipi.</cell>
                     <cell>Caiare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mappo. waroopana Maripa. Chiparipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o. Towtwi. Sarinbugh. Wariwagh.</cell>
                     <cell>Macapowa. Shuracoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Moruga. g. Piara. Chaimerago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Iaos. Arwaccas.</cell>
                     <cell>Coopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roore. g. Awiapati. Topoo.</cell>
                     <cell>Manare co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wa. Iarwarema</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>49</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Waini. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Charibes.</cell>
                     <cell>Tocoopoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. g.</cell>
                     <cell>Parana,</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Barima. g. Caitooma. Arooca.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Charibes. Arwaccas.</cell>
                     <cell>Pekwa. g Arwakima</cell>
                     <cell>Anawra. Aparwa. Arracurri.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Amacur. g.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>52</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Aratoori. g. Cawrooma. g. Raleana, or Orenoque. Maipar Itacaponea Owareca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pater. Warucanaſſo.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Ilandes in mouth of Raleana.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:9768:31"/>
            <head>Heere followe the names, of thoſe worthie Spaniardes that haue ſought to diſcouer and conquere <hi>Guiana:</hi> Extracted out of the writinges of <hi>Iuan de Caſtellanos clerigo,</hi> who compiled the booke, intituled, <hi>Primera parte de las Elegias de varones illuſtres de Indias.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1 THe enterpriſe of <hi>Guiana</hi> was vndertaken by <hi>Diego de Ordas</hi> of the kingdom of <hi>Leon,</hi> in the yeare, 1531. He was one of the Captaines of <hi>Cortes</hi> in the conqueſt of <hi>Mexico.</hi> This <hi>Ordas</hi> made his entrance by the riuer of <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> by which we entered, and ſpent fiftie dayes before hee came to the riuer of <hi>Orenoque,</hi> which we paſt in fifteene. Hee named the riuer by which he entred <hi>Viapari;</hi> which name it ſtill retaineth in the Spaniſh deſcriptions. It lieth South from <hi>Trinidado</hi> ſome fiue leagues. He tranſported out of <hi>Spaine</hi> a thouſand ſouldiours. He dyed afterwardes at ſea, in retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an Gorteſo</hi> arriued at the riuer of <hi>Amazones</hi> or <hi>Ore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liano</hi> with three hundred men: Hee marched vp into the countrey. But neither he, nor any of his companie did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Gaſpar de Sylua,</hi> with his two brothers, departed from <hi>Tenerife,</hi> accompanied with 200. men, to aſsiſt <hi>Diego de Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das.</hi> They ſought <hi>El Dorado</hi> by the riuer of <hi>Amazones:</hi> but ſtaying there a ſhort time, they fell down to <hi>Trinidado,</hi> where they all three were buried.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Iuan Gonzales</hi> ſet ſaile from <hi>Trinidado</hi> to diſcouer the <hi>Guiana.</hi> He repoſed himſelfe more on the faith of his guides the on his ſmall number of men He by triall found the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of <hi>Guiana,</hi> ſo far as he entred, to be populous, plentiful of victuall, &amp; rich in gold. Vpon ſuch proofes as he brought with him to make good his report: manie others aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to follow his ſteps.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb facs="tcp:9768:31"/>5. 6. <hi>Philip de Vren,</hi> and after him <hi>Pedro de Limpias,</hi> who both ſucceſsiuelie commaunded the <hi>Almaines,</hi> were leaders in this action. <hi>Limpias</hi> was ſlaine by an Indian Caſsique na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Porima.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>Ieronimo de Ortall</hi> vndetrooke it by the way of <hi>Marecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pana.</hi> After great trauell and his ſubſtance all ſpent, he dyed on the ſudden at <hi>S. Domingo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. 9. <hi>Ximenes,</hi> brother of <hi>Don Ximenes de Queſida</hi> the <hi>Lantado,</hi> and <hi>Pedro de Oſuq,</hi> were both at ſundrie times in the ſame queſt.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Father <hi>Iala,</hi> a Frier, taking with him onelie one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, and ſome Indian guides paſſed into the prouinces of <hi>Guiana.</hi> He returned with good intelligence, &amp; brought with him Eagles, Idols, and other iewels of golde. An. 1560. He aſſayed the ſecond time to paſſe in like maner, but was ſlaine by the Indians.</p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>Hernandes de Serpa</hi> alſo vndertooke it. The Indians of <hi>Cumanawgoto</hi> killed him, and defeated his Armie.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Afterwards, <hi>Diego de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>argas,</hi> and his ſonne <hi>Don Iuan</hi> followed this enterpriſe, and at their firſt ſetting out, were ſlaine by the Indians.</p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>Caceres</hi> vndertooke this diſcouerie from <hi>Nueuo Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no de Granada.</hi> He came no neerer to it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Matachines,</hi> which borders vpon the ſaid kingdom of <hi>Granada:</hi> He reſted there and peopled that place.</p>
            <p n="14">14 It was alſo attempted by <hi>Alonzo de Herera,</hi> at two ſeuerall times. He endured great miſerie, but neuer entred one league into the countrey. He ſought it by <hi>Wia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pari,</hi> or <hi>Amana,</hi> and was at laſt ſlaine by a nation of Indians called <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aguas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15 It was alſo vndertaken by <hi>Antonio Sedenno,</hi> with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Herera</hi> and <hi>Augustine Delgado</hi> ioyned in the conqueſt of <hi>Trinidado,</hi> againſt <hi>Bawcunar</hi> a famous king of that place. He paſſed by <hi>Marecupana</hi> in the yeare 1536. to diſcouer <hi>El Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rado</hi> with 500. choſen men. In this iourny he got much gold
<pb facs="tcp:9768:32"/>
and tooke manie Indian priſoners; whome he manacled in yrons, manie of them died as they were led in the way. The Tygres being fleſhed on thoſe dead carkaſſes, aſſaulted the Spaniards, who with much trouble hardlie defended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from them. <hi>Sedenno</hi> was buried within the precinct of the Empire neere the head of the riuer <hi>Tinados.</hi> Moſt of his people periſhed likewiſe.</p>
            <p n="16">16 <hi>Augustine Delgado</hi> ſearched the country to the ſouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of <hi>Cumanawgoto</hi> with 53. footmen and three horſmen. The warres that were then between the Indians of the vale, and thoſe of the mountaines, ſerued well for his purpoſe. By which occaſion he found meanes to paſſe ſo farre vntill hee came to an Indian Caſſique, named <hi>Garamentall,</hi> who enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained him with al kindnes. And gaue him for a preſent ſome rich iewels of gold: ſix ſeemlie Pages: ten young ſlaues, and three Nymphes verie beautifull, which bore the names of three prouinces from whence they were ſent to <hi>Garamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,</hi> cheife Commander of all that countrey. Their names were, <hi>Guanba, Gotoguane,</hi> and <hi>Matarare.</hi> Theſe prouinces are of an excellent temperature, verie healthful, and haue an admirable influence in producing beautifull women. The Spaniards afterwards to requite the manifold curteſies that they receiued in that countrey, tooke and caried away be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all the gold that they could get, al the Indians that they could lay hold on: they conueyed them in yrons to <hi>Cubag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua</hi> and ſolde them for ſlaues. <hi>Delgado</hi> afterwards was ſhot in the eie by an Indian: of which hurt he died.</p>
            <p n="17">17 <hi>Diego de Loſada,</hi> ſucceeded in his brothers place. Hee had manie more men; who in the end waſted themſelues in mutinies: thoſe that liued returned to <hi>Cubugua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18 <hi>Reynoſo</hi> vndertooke this iourney: but hauing endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red exceeding troubles, in the diſcomfort of his minde, hee gaue it ouer and was buried in <hi>Hispaniola.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19 <hi>Pedro de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſua,</hi> in the yeare 1560. ſought it with 400 Spaniards, by the riuer <hi>Oreliano.</hi> He imbarqued his men in
<pb facs="tcp:9768:32"/>
the country of the <hi>Moti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ones.</hi> As they paſſed downe the riuer, they found Synamon trees. His men murdered him and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward the ſaid rebels beheaded Lady <hi>Anes</hi> his wife, who forſooke not her Lord in all his trauels vnto death.</p>
            <p n="20">20 Fryer <hi>Francis Monteſinos,</hi> was in the prouince of <hi>Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupana</hi> with 100. ſouldiors bound for the <hi>Guiana,</hi> when <hi>Lope Aguirri</hi> the Tyrant made inſurrection in all thoſe partes of the Indies. What became of this intended iourney is not expreſſed.</p>
            <p>In the diſcouerie of <hi>Guiana,</hi> you may read both of <hi>Orelia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> who diſcouered the riuer of <hi>Amazones</hi> An. 1510. and of <hi>Berreo,</hi> with others that haue trode this maze, and loſt them ſelues in ſeeking to find this countrie.</p>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <head>An aduertiſment to the Reader.</head>
               <p>IN this Breuiarie, the names onlie are compriſed of ſuch as being led with the generall fame of <hi>Guiana,</hi> haue endeuoured to diſcouer &amp; poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe it. The whole hiſtories are long and cannot ſuddenlie be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or Engliſhed at large, as we in theſe Elegies find them. It may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſeeme ſtrange and incredible, that ſo manie Caualeros ſhould all faile in this one attempt, ſince in many partes of the Indies, far ſmaller numbers in ſhorter time haue performed as great matters, and ſubdued mightie Kingdoms: I haue therefore thought it good, here to alleadge thoſe reaſons, which by circumſtance may be gathered to haue beene chief impediments to the Spaniard in this intended ſearch &amp; conqueſt.</p>
               <p>The firſt may be the remoteneſſe or diſtance of their places of <hi>Ronde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow,</hi> from the <hi>Dorado:</hi> which appeare to be foure, <hi>Nueuo Reyno:</hi> the mouth of <hi>Amazones</hi> or <hi>Oreliano. Cubagua,</hi> or the coaſt of the <hi>Carackas:</hi> &amp; <hi>Trinidado.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. From <hi>Moisbanda,</hi> where <hi>Oreliano</hi> hath his head-ſpring to his mouth the Spaniards account it 2000. leagues. <hi>Raleana</hi> riſeth neere the ſaide mountaines in <hi>Moiabanda,</hi> and tributeth his waters to the ſea, not farre from the other: <hi>Guiana</hi> is enuironed with theſe two freſh water ſeas, wher their diſtance is greateſt from their riſinges, and is beſides guarded with impaſſable mountains, which in cloſe &amp; defend it on al partes, excepting <hi>Topiawaries</hi> country. It is no maruel then, if the vigor, heat, &amp; life of thoſe Spaniards, who ſought it from <hi>Nueuo Reyno,</hi> were allayed and ſpent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they came nere it in thoſe long, deſolate, and vncomfortable waies.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From <hi>Cubagua</hi> to ſeek it by ſea, in veſſels of any burthen, is a worke of farre greater labour, then to ſaile directly from <hi>Spaine.</hi> And to paſſe
<pb facs="tcp:9768:33"/>
ouerland is a matter of great difficultie, by reaſon that the Indian Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons inhabiting between the coaſt of the <hi>Carackas</hi> and <hi>Guiana,</hi> being wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and harried with the daylie incurſions of the Spaniards, haue now turned their abuſed patience into furie, refuſing to ſuffer any forces of men to be led through their countries. For the Spaniards trauelling in thoſe parts, when they found not golde anſwerable to their expectation, ouerlaid them with cruelties, tyrannie, and thraldom: forbearing neither men, women friends, nor foes. Which maner of dealing, though in ſome ſort it ſatisfied their deſire of preſent profit: yet hath it otherwiſe done them much harme in hardening and driuing thoſe nations to deſperate reſolutions.</p>
               <p n="3">3 From the mouth of <hi>Oreliano</hi> to ſeeke entrance with any number of men, and to bore a hole through the mountaines, is all one. Neither find we, that any ſeeking it that way, haue at anie time boaſted of their gaines or pleaſurable iourneyes.</p>
               <p n="4">4 From <hi>Trinidado</hi> as the courſe is ſhorteſt: ſo doth it promiſe beſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood of ſucceſſe. Howbeit, impoſſible it is with any veſſell of ordinarie burthen by that way to recouer the riuer of <hi>Raleana.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond. The Spaniards haue bene ſo far from furthering and hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping on another, or admitting partners or coadiutors in the <hi>Guiana</hi> cauſe that amongſt ſo many attempts, from the beginning to the laſt, I cannot find any one, when they were otherwiſe liklieſt to preuaile, free from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, mutinies, and cruel murders amongſt themſelues.</p>
               <p>Thirdly. The Spaniards in this place haue miſt that aduantage, which els where hath ſteeded them in all their conqueſts: namelie, the diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and mutuall warres of the Indians amongſt themſelues, Which of what force it is, may be gathered by the example of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>awcania</hi> in <hi>Peru.</hi> For the Indians of that one prouince containing in circuit not aboue 20. leagues, haue maintained warres aboue theſe 30. yeares, againſt all the Spaniards, and in deſpight of them haue kept their own countrie, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times diſcomforting their enemies in many ſet battayles, burning &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying ſome of their ſtrongeſt townes. The chiefe reaſon wherof I take to be, becauſe no Indian nation was enemy vnto them. And howſoeuer the Spaniards vaunt of their redoubted exploits in the Indies: yet do their owne writings in effect teſtifie, that without the aid of the Indians diuided amongſt rhemſelues, <hi>Mexico, Peru,</hi> and the reſt, had neuer bene Spaniſh.</p>
               <p>Laſtly. I can impute it to no cauſe ſo rightly, as immediately to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine prouidence. For by him princes raigne. And in my beleefe (except we will looke to be warned by miracle from heauen,) we need no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſſurances, then we already haue to perſwade our ſelues that it hath pleaſed our God of his infinit goodneſſe, in his will and purpoſe to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point and reſerue this Empire for vs.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9768:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
